<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Justin Manley</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/feed/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/feed/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Justin Manley</name>
        <email>manleyjster@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2023-03-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>How I learned to stop worrying and love optimization</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/how-I-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-optimization/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/how-I-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-optimization/index.html</id>
    <published>2023-03-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine a traveler stranded in the mountains at night. Somewhere far below, there are valleys with food, warmth, safety. It is pitch-black: no stars, no moon. In order to reach the safety of a valley, the traveler must navigate by feel alone. They slide their feet around, pat the ground to feel which way it slopes, then take a step in the direction of steepest descent, always following the gradient of the land. If the traveler is lucky and the landscape accommodating, gradient descent will bring them eventually out of the mountains.</p>
<p>I first heard this parable in a class on training neural networks to recognize objects in images. We would feed in an image, and the network would guess whether the image showed a horse or a bird or a dog or a frog. In our attempts to train the network, we always began with a sort of template, a structure with many empty slots, each slot meant to hold a single number. By filling the slots with different numbers, we could create different versions of our neural network. To make a prediction, the neural network would add and multiply the numbers in its slots together with the image we fed it. After the network made a prediction, we calculated how far it had been from the truth. This number, which we called the loss, told us how good that particular version of the network was. Even the tiny network we worked with had more than a hundred thousand slots. We never knew which way of filling the network’s slots would enable it to guess correctly, so we picked the numbers randomly to begin with. From there, we began to search, looking for a version of the network with a lower loss.</p>
<p>We sought the optimal network using an algorithm called gradient descent. Instead of mountains and valleys, we explored the optimization landscape of the neural network. In this abstract mathematical space, each point represented a different version of the neural network, while the network’s loss determined the elevation at that point. Assigned to implement and optimize neural networks for homework, I would flick back and forth between my code and an elevation profile showing the optimization as it unfolded in real-time. If the optimization went well, this graph would start high on the left side of the screen and descend towards the right as the optimization progressed. Looking at the graph, watching the network explore the unknown landscape of itself, I began to feel as though I, too, was a traveler in the darkness.</p>
<p>Optimization is an essential part of the vocabulary of technological hype. In self-help books it appears as a foolproof method for success. In advertising, the promise that a product has been optimized assures the purchaser that its development and production have been scientific and systematic. In the everyday settings where it is most often encountered, optimization is about efficiency and perfection. But after a few weeks of the neural network class, it meant something different to me. The more I spent time actually optimizing things, the more the word made me think of the vastness of the unknown, the necessity of trying things before judging them, and the connectedness of everything in the world to everything else. Optimization, I found, made efficiency and perfection delightfully irrelevant.</p>
<p class="divider">
◊
</p>
<p>My earliest memory of being optimized is from middle school, when my dad enrolled me and my sister in an after-school math program. There was no teaching or tutoring in this program. Instead, I was trained through brute repetition. Each week, I received a bundle of worksheets, one packet for each day. The packets were full of arithmetic problems, printed in a grid on both sides of each sheet. The hypothesis seemed to be that the sheer quantity of problems would gradually and irresistibly rewire my brain, turn me into a machine which could intuitively, effortlessly, produce the answer to any arithmetic problem. Problems in, answers out — and me in the middle, changing bit by bit, slowly becoming a more perfect calculator. Any conscious arithmetical understanding I might develop was expected to emerge spontaneously from the problems themselves. Once a week, I went into the after-school program’s office, an underground room in the back of a strip mall, where I completed another worksheet, a weekly assessment. My score on this assessment measured my ongoing transformation into a human calculator.</p>
<p>I studied math in college, then took a job as a software engineer at Google. I was grateful to have a job that would help me pay off my hundred thousand dollars of student debt. Still, I wanted more. I had believed the company’s recruiting slogans, had expected to make computers do things that felt like magic, things the world had never seen before. Instead, my work felt routine and inconsequential. One of tens of thousands of engineers, I felt like a cog in a vast machine. I felt interchangeable.</p>
<p>This was because the kind of software I had been hired to write — “traditional” computer programs made of if-statements and for-loops — had become distinctly unfashionable within the company. Instead, everyone was obsessed with neural networks, computer programs loosely inspired by the biological structure of the human brain. Google was already using neural networks to recognize cats in YouTube videos, recognize speech, and suggest email responses. The company’s star researchers were all working on the technology, and every week they would take the stage at all-hands meetings to share progress on their latest projects: beautifying photographs, proving mathematical theorems, improvising Bach harmonies. Across the street from where I worked, there was a room full of camera-equipped robot arms controlled by neural networks learning hand-eye coordination. Elsewhere in the company, another team was working on using neural networks to automate conventional software engineering.</p>
<p>Feeling envious and excited and a little threatened, I enrolled in a course to learn how the new type of computer program worked. It was here that I learned to march the neural network through the landscape of all possible versions of itself. The network’s loss determined the landscape’s elevation, meaning that the least-bad version of the network would be found at the lowest point in this landscape, the bottom of its deepest valley. At each point along this march, the algorithm would calculate how the landscape sloped around the network’s current position, then direct the network to take a step in the direction of steepest descent, <a href="http://www.denizyuret.com/2015/03/alec-radfords-animations-for.html">always following the gradient of the land</a>. At each step, the algorithm knew only where it was and where it had been. Extrapolating even a few steps ahead was infeasible. Surveying the landscape from some high point in order to plan the descent was out of the question. The problem was that the optimization landscape was unimaginably vast: not vast in extent, like Siberia or the Sahara, but in dimension. The two dimensions of east/west and north/south along the earth’s surface, are nothing compared to the tens of thousands of directions (one for each slot) in the optimization landscape of even a small neural network. Every additional direction multiplied the number of choices. Unable to look ahead, it was as though the algorithm traversed the landscape in pitch-darkness, navigating by feel alone.</p>
<p>The instructors cautioned that optimizing neural networks was uncertain and unpredictable: there was always a possibility of failure. If the algorithm marched the network out onto a plateau, the flatness of its surroundings would provide no signals about which way to turn, and it would come to a standstill; if into a region of steep cliffs, the network would undergo a kind of neural death as too-strong signals filled its slots with infinities. Or it might get stuck in a high valley, the landscape curving upwards all around it, trapping it in place: a dreaded local optimum. Our instructors offered folk wisdom for navigating these situations, strategies that seemed to work, even though scientists couldn’t yet explain why. They explained how to assess the health of an ongoing optimization, how to read its loss curve like an augury and diagnose the likely causes of failure. Above all, they counseled us to develop our own intuitions for the likely paths different algorithms would take or how alterations to the network’s mathematical structure might reshape its optimization landscape. I found the exploratory and improvisational spirit of their guidance invigorating.</p>
<p>Whenever I talked to my sister on the phone, she would inevitably ask me what I planned to do next: how long I planned to stay at my job, whether my boyfriend and I would stay together, when I would move back east. I resented these questions and felt somehow ashamed for not having the answers. For years, I had done everything I was supposed to: achieved high test scores and good grades, gotten into a good college, secured a stable, professional job. But beyond hitting these external targets, I had drifted, without a focus or goal. I hadn’t needed one. Now that I had some autonomy, I was realizing I didn’t know how to articulate what I wanted from life. I was pursuing a feeling rather than a credential.</p>
<p>Studying neural networks, I noticed that a network’s goal was defined obliquely in terms of a large dataset of examples, rather than a tidy formula. Indeed, I learned, neural networks were most useful for pursuing goals which could not be expressed neatly. Training a neural network for homework, I observed the way it moved towards its incorporeal, unconsolidated goal in tiny increments, never certain of its exact destination. This, I thought, was how I had been moving through life. In life, this strategy seemed like aimless drifting. But here, it worked. In just the few minutes since I started training the network, the loss had gone down. The network was learning, and I had numbers to prove it. Seeing its quantifiable success eased the sense of inadequacy I felt at not having a blueprint for my future.</p>
<p>The course wasn’t easy. I struggled on every assignment, filling sheets of paper with calculations before arriving at a solution I could translate into code. I stayed up late many nights, testing my equations and trying to optimize the network. Many times, the optimization failed because of some mistake I had made in one of the many equations. I would track down the error, fix it, and try again. Despite my best efforts, I received poor grades on the assignments. This course was my first serious foray into mathematics after graduating from college, and part of my rationale for enrolling was to prove that my poor grades in my college had been the result of circumstances, rather than a verdict on my abilities. But when I tried my best and still didn’t do well, I was tempted to view my performance as confirmation of my incorrigible intellectual inferiority. My housemate was taking the same course, and he seemed to get top marks easily: proof (so my inner self whispered) that my abilities were second-rate.</p>
<p>Haunted by the suspicion of my own unalterable mediocrity, I found it strangely comforting to watch the loss curve downwards as I optimized a neural network. Here it was: real improvement, before my eyes, rigorous and quantifiable. Even I, skeptical by nature, could hardly disbelieve the evidence for improvability when I had implemented it myself and run it on my own computer. If my neural network could become better, then surely so could I.</p>
<p>After I completed the course, I mentioned to my boss that I wanted to take another one, a mathematics course entirely focused on optimization theory. He laughed: “why would you want to do that?” He told me I’d surely be able to perform any optimization I needed with some off-the-shelf software library, said there was no need to understand how it actually worked. I didn’t know how to tell him that when I was learning about optimization, I felt like I was learning about life.</p>
<p class="divider">
◊
</p>
<p>Optimization is the mobilization of measurement in the service of desire. It thrives on feedback loops, the tighter the better. In the last two decades, the rise of mobile personal computing has produced an unprecedented abundance of feedback. Today, our devices contain sensors, computers, and rich output devices: just what is needed to measure our means and computationally coordinate them in pursuit of quantified ends. When I shift my bedtime so that my smart watch will rate my sleep more highly, I am optimizing myself. When I order groceries online or catch a ride through an app, I know the app is using my fees and my feedback to optimize the driver’s behavior. When I go to work I am optimized in turn by my employer using software for “continuous performance management.”</p>
<p>The idea of optimization was first articulated during World War II by a US Air Force statistician named George Dantzig. Dantzig’s group developed programs for assigning military personnel to tasks and deciding how supplies and weapons should be moved around. Their programs produced instructions for tens of thousands of people; Dantzig later described this effort as the equivalent of running the economy of a small nation.</p>
<p>During the war, Dantzig came to view the many varied planning problems he faced as essentially similar abstract problems of means and ends, and he sought a general method for reconciling the two. His great innovation, first articulated in a 1947 lecture, was to express the attainment of a desired end as a single number calculated in terms of the available means. Dantzig called this calculation an objective function, and he developed an algorithm for discovering the values which would maximize or minimize a particular objective function in order to reveal the best means to achieve a desired end. It was this idea, of expressing a goal as a number and then using that number to guide action towards the goal, which would eventually become known as optimization.</p>
<p>In the decades following Dantzig’s 1947 paper, optimization was embraced enthusiastically by the military, chemicals manufacturers, and airlines. It quietly transformed food, health, and travel: people knowing nothing of optimization nevertheless ate cattle and poultry raised on a mix of different feeds optimized to deliver calories as cheaply as possible. They filled up their cars with gasoline blended from different petroleum products optimized to produce an acceptable freezing point, vapor pressure, and octane rating, all again at the lowest possible cost. But despite its widespread adoption in industry, optimization remained esoteric. When, in the late 1950s, one of Dantzig’s students assembled an early textbook on the subject, publisher after publisher rejected it, doubtful it would find an audience. Dantzig’s collaborators understood the mathematics of optimization better than anyone else in the world. But even they were skeptical when he told them he was toying with using optimization to direct his own life, starting with an algorithmically-generated weight-loss diet. One collaborator, himself a famous mathematician, admonished Dantzig that optimization was meant to be used on other people, not on oneself.</p>
<p class="divider">
◊
</p>
<p>The first artifacts of optimization to capture my attention were a series of images I saw at an art exhibition. The images had been created using a then-nine-month-old technique called DeepDream. Their creators had first trained a neural network to recognize objects in images the same way I would in class several years later. Then, they had fixed the numbers inside the network, and turned the whole thing backwards, treating the network’s input as a grid of empty slots, one for each pixel. They used optimization to fill those slots with numbers which would maximize the image’s resemblance (as assessed by the neural network) to some object.</p>
<p>The DeepDream exhibition was full of strange and captivating images. One picture showed a landscape dotted with palaces, each set in the middle of a circular lawn mowed in swirls, each swirl forming a smaller circular lawn around a smaller palace. I could not tell whether the palaces which proliferated along the edges of the large swirls were tiny, or very far away. Near and far seemed strangely interleaved, as though the picture showed something much larger than an ordinary three-dimensional landscape.</p>
<p>In the years after DeepDream was first developed, scientists used <a href="https://distill.pub/2017/feature-visualization">the technique</a> to build an atlas of the patterns and objects recognized by each neuron in one of the most widely-used visual recognition networks. Browsing the atlas, one image catches my eye: a pattern like chicken wire woven from live earthworms, sinuous and slippery. The technique produces not a single archetypal earthworm, but a never-ending sea. Optimization multiplies the subject of the image until everything else is squeezed out. Every pixel is pressed into service. And the patterns never repeat: every pinkish-brown curve is unique. This is not homogeneity, but totality. Not the same earthworm repeated ad infinitum, but all the earthworms which ever existed — all the earthworms which might ever exist — heaped together until they obscure everything else.</p>
<p>I love watching these images form. The process starts with white noise, like static on a television screen. Slowly, patterns or shapes start to emerge, like figures coming out a thick fog. They are gray and indistinct at first, but become increasingly sharp and colorful as the optimization progresses. Optimization coaxes structure and meaning and order out of the chaos.</p>
<p>Some of the DeepDream images in the original exhibition <a href="https://miketyka.com/?p=SaxophoneDreams">almost</a> <a href="https://miketyka.com/?p=StyleIsViolins">resembled</a> Cubist paintings by Picasso or Braque. Another <a href="https://miketyka.com/?p=CastlesInTheSkyWithDiamonds">reminded me</a> of van Gogh’s Starry Night. Looking at these pictures, I wondered whether the optimization process which produced them had anything in common with the way humans made art. Perhaps the neuron being maximized by the DeepDream algorithm might be like a feeling the human artist sought to express, and optimization the artistic process of iteratively refining an expression until it felt true.</p>
<p>When I was not attending exhibitions of optimized pictures, I lurked on arXiv, a website where neural network researchers share their work. I filled my browser tabs with scientific papers about neural network architectures and objective functions and optimization landscapes, papers I could only half-understand, but devoured anyway. Many of these papers came with accompanying video demonstrations. I’ve watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hx_bgoTF7bs">one of these</a> many times. It shows a series of cartoon figures running through various simulated obstacle courses. The research paper explains that the figures were set on their obstacle courses without any knowledge of how to operate their limbs and scored on how far they could get through the obstacle course without falling down. The neural networks which controlled the figures’ movements learned to run by optimizing this score. At every step, when the neural network was scored on how far its body had traveled, numbers flowed backwards through the network. The impact of every trip-up, every overbalancing, every overlooked obstacle was propagated from the macro-scale to the micro. Every neuron informed its neighbors how they should respond differently next time to make the body move faster and farther.</p>
<p>In the video, one cartoon figure leaps over gaps in the terrain like a hurdler: push-off perfectly timed, leading foot outstretched to make contact with the ground on the other side. Faced with a floating platform stretching across the course at chest-height, it bends backwards smoothly, doing the limbo without slowing down. Another figure runs up a staircase with long, even strides. At the top, hidden from view until a few moments before, there is a large pit. The cartoon figure makes a heroic leap and almost overbalances when its front foot touches the ground on the other side, but by swinging its arms up is able to recover its balance without breaking stride. Its movements look graceful and easy. Sometimes when I’m watching the video, I scrub backwards after watching the humanoid figure leap over the pit, just for the pleasure of seeing it again.</p>
<p class="divider">
◊
</p>
<p>There are many ways of turning reading and writing into optimization problems. The most common approach is to predict the next word in a text, given all the words that have come before. Other approaches mask out words randomly and try to guess the missing words, or scramble words in a sentence and attempt to unscramble them. All of these are ways of turning reading into a game, an activity whose success or failure can be quantified. Texts are scrambled, erased, or corrupted, and it is always the job of the neural network to recover the human original.</p>
<p>In the early 1950s, George Dantzig’s doctor advised Dantzig that he was overweight and should go on a diet. Naturally, Dantzig’s first instinct was to <a href="https://gwern.net/doc/statistics/decision/1990-dantzig.pdf">approach his doctor-ordered diet as an optimization problem</a>. He drew up a table of ingredients and fed the punch cards into RAND’s IBM 701 mainframe (one of only nineteen then in existence). On the first day, the computer dictated an optimal diet of 500 gallons of vinegar per day; on the second, 200 bouillon cubes; on the third, two pounds of bran; and on the fourth, two pounds of blackstrap molasses. On the fifth day, Dantzig abandoned his optimized diet.</p>
<p>Like Dantzig, I have dabbled in self-optimization. I wanted to become a better writer and thought I might cleverly circumvent the labor of self-improvement by fabricating an improved version of my writerly self. Over several weeks one summer, I fine-tuned a neural network on a decade of my own writing: art criticism, diaries, a draft of this essay. With one line of code, I downloaded a pretrained model. Another line of code initialized the optimization. I let it run, then inspected the results.</p>
<p>The network picked up my favorite subjects: art, memories of cooking with friends, confessions about friction with coworkers, long ambivalent interrogations of relationships. It also picked up my stylistic tics: the obsessive introspection of my diaries and art criticism. It didn’t satisfy me, though. The text I generated came without effort, but was uninspiring. It showed me my past self when what I wanted was my future.</p>
<p>The comic failure of Dantzig’s own diet optimization resulted inevitably from the naivety of his optimization objective. His goal was sensible enough: he sought to maximize the feeling of fullness after each meal so he could eat as little as possible and still feel satisfied. In modern terms, he wanted a low-calorie-density diet. But the way Dantzig made this vague notion measurable was absurd. He calculated for each food its percentage of solid (non-water) content, and scored each diet according to the weighted solid content of all its food — as though water were unnecessary and all edible solids equivalent in their nutritional and content. In optimizing, he sought the diet with the highest score. The resulting diets were, as they say in computer science, a case of “garbage in, garbage out.” But although Dantzig quickly abandoned his optimized diet, he never abandoned optimization. Indeed, for the next fifty years, right until his death in 2005, optimization was the primary focus of Dantzig’s life.</p>
<p>Even before I saw the results of my optimized writing, I knew the optimization objective I was using was a caricature no less ridiculous than Dantzig’s. I wanted my writing to respond to the world with sensitivity and to creatively imagine new worlds, but I trained it only to imitate what already exists. After a few weeks, I too abandoned the experiment. Still, I have not been able to bring myself to abandon optimization itself.</p>
<p>Now, instead of actually applying optimization to my life, I think in terms of optimization. I fall back on metaphor. I treat fuzzy, underspecified desires as though they might be optimizable. I imagine applying algorithms to situations which are unmeasured or unmeasurable. I embrace optimization not as a means of action, but as a way of thinking, a way of seeing.</p>
<p>As I write this, I have found myself often thinking about the activity of writing as a kind of optimization. I imagine optimizing without constraining myself to readily available datasets or known techniques. Freed of the constraints of implementation feasibility, I imagine a different optimization process, one which feels more truthful to my own experience. When I write, I am trying to find a match between an arrangement of words on a page and something inside me, an inchoate feeling or an idea. If I am troubled or uncertain, I write to bring about a change within myself, a sense of resolution. Working incrementally, rewriting a sentence here, a paragraph there, I try to move my whole manuscript towards something I can’t yet articulate, but will know when I see it. I think of myself as optimizing the feeling of rightness in the writing. I recall DeepDream images emerging out of multicolored static and hope that what I am doing will create order and meaning out of the jumble of words on the page in front of me. I cannot implement this optimization. But in my head, I am living it. I have become the optimizer, and I have become the network through which optimization flows.</p>
<h3 id="notes">Notes</h3>
<p class="text-secondary">
I wrote this between April 2020 and May 2021 and returned to it on and off through September 2022, though it was only posted in the spring of 2023.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
Thanks to Ivy Lau, Abigail Kelly, and Joseph Bolling, who listened to drafts of this essay on two 15-hour drives between San Francisco and Washington State. Thanks to <a href="https://history.fas.harvard.edu/people/ione-barrows">Ione Barrows</a> and Mike Webb for their feedback, and to <a href="https://twitter.com/jaizuss_">Julia Aizuss</a> at <a href="https://thepointmag.com"><em>The Point</em></a> for holding me to a high standard of emotional accuracy.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
The header GIF is an excerpt from the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hx_bgoTF7bs">video</a> accompanying the paper “Emergence of Locomotion Behaviours in Rich Environments.”
</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>I, Robot / You, Robot: Alan Rath and the Choreography of Consciousness</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/alan-rath-again/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/alan-rath-again/index.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two robotic arms dance against a white wall. The robots flirt with each other, waving, tickling, stroking, kissing. They are elegant and uncanny: the robots strike a bodybuilder’s pose, flexing, then twirl like octopus tentacles before straightening out into a pair of long human legs. The robotic arms belong to an artwork called <em>Again</em>, completed in 2017 by artist Alan Rath, and as I watch their movements, I feel that I am facing a pair of creatures animated by a strange new form of consciousness.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VGeNJs7VLuQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p><em>Again</em> is the latest installment in Rath’s thirty-year engagement with robotic selfhood and otherness. Rath graduated from MIT with a degree in electrical engineering in 1982 and started working in the computer graphics industry near Boston. A few months later, he quit his job and moved to Oakland, California to make electronic art (<a href="https://www.sfgate.com/entertainment/article/Interview-Alan-Rath-3002857.php">electronic parts were cheaper in the Bay Area than anywhere else</a>). Rath began making electronic sculptures in 1984: digital counters, stands of pulsing speakers, and CRT screens showing disembodied hands and lips and eyes. These earliest sculptures play at being creatures in their own right (not merely machines). <em>Birdcage</em> (1985), <em>Voyeur</em> (1986), and <em>Hound</em> (1990) are wonderful examples of this “creaturely” aesthetic. In these sculptures, schematic animal forms and videos of human body parts suggest active awareness. A pair of eyes flicking from side to side and a dog with its nose to the ground are both searching for something. Searching is always an intentional act – one that is directed towards an object or an outcome in the world. It is the seeming intentionality of these early sculptures that makes them interesting.</p>
<p>Rath’s early work presents the image of an unsociable, single-purpose awareness. Isolation and a relentless outward-facing gaze limit the possibility of sympathetic identification with the machines. A furrowed brow or a falling tear would hint at the motives for the search depicted in these sculptures. <em>Voyeur</em> has neither furrow nor brow, and certainly no tears. Even without such dramatic tics, the eyes might still convey emotion if it were not for the tight crop of the video. Plucked out of the face, these orphaned eyes are missing the facial cues that we normally use to decode emotion. The result is an impression of naked intentionality without thoughts or feelings – a remarkable feat.</p>
<p>The roving eyes and sniffing noses of Rath’s early sculptures are entirely outward-focused (that is, they seem always to attend to the current visitor, and nothing else). They have the appeal of surveillance agents: they are interesting to me mainly because they are interested in me. These sculptures might still transcend the emptiness of the one-sided surveillance stare if they had companions to interact with. Watching interactions between creatures which are similar to each other invites us to imagine their experience of each other. But each of these sculptures is an endling, the sole exemplar of its kind. Uniqueness makes each sculpture appear as a freak-show oddity, rather than a peer.</p>
<p>Rath began in the early nineties to explore relationships between pairs of subjects, still within static, one-piece sculptures. His <em>Vanity</em> (1992) shows a man on a CRT screen looking at his own image in a bathroom mirror. The mirror departs from the surveilling stares of Rath’s earlier works by allowing the sculpture’s gaze to turn inward. Like the early video sculptures, this piece considers only a single, narrow aspect of consciousness (in vanity, awareness of the self extinguishes all other modes of awareness). <em>Couple</em> (1992), <em>Family</em> (1994) and <em>Togetherness II</em> (1995) are video sculptures which join multiple subjects in dialog. In these sculptures, screens showing moving lips and contorted faces are bound together by chains and ropes and clamps. Each reads as a single multi-faced, almost schizophrenic object. This is the beginning of a shift from individuals to relationships.</p>
<p>In the years between 1993 and 1998, Rath’s interest in portraying relationships between creatures grew into an obsession. During this period, Rath also began in earnest to make robotic sculptures, artful machines which sense and move autonomously. He designed these machines to interact with each other, and presented them together in ensembles. <em>Robot Dance</em> (1995), <em>Meet Me At the Corner</em> (1998), and <em>One Track Minds</em> (1998) each show two identical figures moving through choreographies of mutual discovery. In <em>Corner</em> and the <em>Dance</em>, two long triangular figures are mounted on the wall, where they twirl and stretch. In <em>One Track Minds</em>, the pair moves back and forth along a 40-foot track, chasing and embracing. Rath also made larger heterogeneous ensembles during this time, like <em>Pair</em> (1998) and <em>Friends and Acquaintances</em> (1998), in which robots with long unrolling metal tapes and feather-tipped arms probe the cavities and crevices in their counterparts. With these works, Rath finally traces the full outlines of his approach to self and otherness.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oW2nr9VeEas?start=3023" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p><em>Robot Dance</em> is the progenitor of <em>Again</em>, the pair of robotic arms which I saw flirting on the wall at Hosfelt Gallery in 2017. The newer piece has the same overall form and nearly the same choreography as <em>Robot Dance</em>. But where <em>Robot Dance</em> is clumsy and jerky, <em>Again</em> is elegant. The newer work far surpasses its original. <em>Again</em> is the pinnacle (thus far) of Rath’s exploration of self, other, and consciousness. Rath doesn’t use these words to describe his work. Instead, he talks about autonomy and sensing – the language of the roboticist, rather than the philosopher. Yet one cannot appreciate Rath’s robotic sculptures without taking self, other, and consciousness seriously.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4TLFSUI4kOs?start=1095" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>Two contradictory views of consciousness divide contemporary philosophers of mind. On one account, consciousness is the name we give to our subjective experience of the world — the fact that mere existence feels like anything at all.<sup><a href="#subjective-experience">1</a></sup> Consciousness is what gives me a self. This view matches the intuition that I am the only person who can vouch for my own experience. At the same time, making consciousness utterly private and incommunicable creates a conundrum. The assumption that others have experience like my own is the foundation of all social life. I make sense of the behavior of others through analogy to myself. It is through this assumption of similarity that empathy, persuasion, and humor are possible at all. Yet, according to the first-person view of consciousness, it is impossible for me to know whether anyone else is conscious. This conclusion is useless at best and paralyzing at worst.</p>
<p>A popular alternative approach holds that a thing is conscious if its behavior is most easily predicted using a vocabulary of thoughts, beliefs, emotions, and intentions. Philosopher Daniel Dennett, who champions this view, calls it the intentional stance.<sup><a href="#subjective-experience">2</a></sup> This definition is favored by scientists of mind – psychologists and neuroscientists – for the way that it makes consciousness observable and measurable. If the first-person theory of consciousness centers on the self, the intentional stance centers on the other. Certainly it resolves the conundrum of the first-person view of consciousness – the unknowability of other minds. Yet it does so by ignoring that which is most essential to the common-sense understanding of consciousness, namely its origin in personal experience.</p>
<p>The question of consciousness crystallizes the old, persistent tension between subjective and scientific ways of knowing. This is why the debate between the two dominant views of consciousness is a bitter holy war among philosophers, with each side insisting that its theory alone is correct and all others are nonsense. It is clear that each theory of consciousness has serious flaws. Yet I find both to be useful, if one can bear the uncertainty of entertaining two contradictory theories at the same time. An idealistic (or naive) mind can adopt Dennett’s intentional stance and the scientific findings it has encouraged, and still hope to illuminate the private mystery of experience. <em>Again</em> invites just such a hybrid approach through episodes of movement that blur the distinction between self and other.</p>
<p>The best place to view <em>Again</em> is from about fifteen feet back. From there, I have the uncomfortable impression – it can be described in no other way – of being in the presence of a pair of mechanical creatures conscious of their environment and of each other. In an awareness that goes beyond that of electronic sensors, these creatures seem to have feelings towards each other: wariness, curiosity, anticipation. There is something embarrassing in the persistence of <em>Again</em>’s anthropomorphic fantasy — perhaps its scientific implausibility (we are far from understanding consciousness, let alone creating it), or its seeming regression to illusionism as the standard of art. This is an old artist’s trick: take a forgotten everyday phenomenon and relocate it to a new context in order to stir fresh appreciation. In facing <em>Again</em>, we become newly aware of the intentional stance and of how little we are able to explain or justify its application.</p>
<p><em>Again</em> conveys the impression of consciousness through a novel vocabulary of abstract gestures. Designed for the infinitely-rotatable jointed arms of <em>Again</em>, this vocabulary produces a dance no human could perform. The movements generate the meaning of this work.</p>
<p>Each gesture in <em>Again</em> evokes a different animal form: a human leg; an octopus tentacle; the beak of a long-necked bird; a human arm curling and flexing. The familiarity of these forms creates a sense of life within each brief episode of movement. The transitions between episodes are grotesque; the human leg contorts and twirls unnaturally to become an arm, which twists against itself, snakelike, to become something else entirely. These juxtapositions discourage attachment to any particular biological metaphor. Instead, the montage focuses attention on the commonalities shared among organisms. The result is a novel synthetic whole, a lifelike machine which is unlike any particular animal.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VTNmLt7QX8E" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>It is important that the figures in <em>Again</em> are embodied. In one early study of anthropomorphism, psychologists Fritz Heider &amp; Marianne Simmel showed subjects an animation of abstract geometric shapes. Subjects narrated the animation by giving the abstract shapes emotions and intentions. I see intentionality in both the animation in the study and in <em>Again</em>. Yet I am sharply aware that the shapes in Heider &amp; Simmel’s animation are merely representations of consciousness, not the real thing. My awareness of this artifice limits the emotional scope of the encounter between Heider &amp; Simmel’s shapes. The embodiment of the figures in <em>Again</em> collapses the distance between the representation and reality of intentionality. The arms move in a plane, but have enough depth to deny the flatness of the moving image. As a result, <em>Again</em> feels authentic in a way that mere animations do not. This is key to the emotive power of the sculpture (and the main reason that videos of Rath’s robots are always less impressive than the real thing).</p>
<p>A single gesture in <em>Again</em> – a twirl, a wave – is enough to suggest life. The impression of consciousness, on the other hand, comes from the relationship between the two figures. Consciousness in humans is not static – it develops, and it does so in a social context. Newborn babies can mimic the facial expressions of adults within hours of birth,<sup><a href="#mimicking-facial-expressions">3</a></sup> but it takes four years for children to develop a full awareness of self and other.<sup><a href="#full-awareness">4</a></sup> It is in babies that we see consciousness at its simplest, unencumbered by sophisticated language or culture. At this early, pre-linguistic stage, infants develop their awareness of self and other through gestural exchanges: pointing, mirroring, sharing attention with adults. These same patterns of interaction structure the choreography of <em>Again</em>.</p>
<p>As the robotic figures move, they often mirror each other’s motions. Some reflections are simple, as when the figures mirror each other across the vertical line midway between them or over the horizontal line that connects their bases. Others are more subtle: often, the axis of reflection runs through the largest arm segment and rotates along with it. Occasionally, the two figures are related by a point reflection. Most symmetries of shapes on a flat surface can be realized by sliding the shapes around until they overlap. Reflections are different. To demonstrate a reflection, one must lift up the object and flip it over. This additional step challenges the mind’s eye<sup><a href="#cognitive-labor-symmetry">5</a></sup>. It is easy to recognize the similarity of the two figures in <em>Again</em>, but it takes work to reconcile them. The mirror symmetries in <em>Again</em> are tantalizing; they mark the similarity and the irreconcilable difference between the two identical figures. It is impossible to tell which movements come first — which figure is “real” and which is merely the mirror image.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TRSXpdsEWwQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
<figcaption>
Rath’s <em>Vanity</em> (1992) shows a face confronting itself in the mirror.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>A famous series of experiments in psychology explore the way that animals respond to their mirror images. In these experiments, researchers secretly mark the subject’s forehead with a patch of color, then observe whether subjects touch the mark on their forehead when they see it in the mirror. Many psychologists treat this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirror_test">“mirror test”</a> as an indicator of self-awareness. Human babies typically pass the mirror test at eighteen months. Dolphins, magpies, chimpanzees, and other great apes have also passed the mirror test. Most animals fail, either ignoring their mirror image, or treating it as another member of their own species. The mirror plumbs its user for the ability to distinguish between self, other, and mere representation. Episodes of symmetric movement in <em>Again</em> evoke the mirror test. Yet the figures in <em>Again</em> move smoothly between encounters of self with self (mirror), and self with other (dialog). These transitions blur the boundaries between the two, depicting a self and other which are thoroughly entangled. In picturing a continuum between self and other, <em>Again</em> suggests that the opposing theories of consciousness which center on self and other might also meet somewhere in the middle.</p>
<p>The figures in <em>Again</em> seem most individual and most aware of each other when their gestures become conversational. In one such sequence, they reach out towards each other, almost fully extended. From this position, they take turns to wave at each other, waggling their smallest segments. After exchanging gestures, they swivel to a new position, and repeat. In another sequence, one of the arms hangs motionless, crooked in a sideways “v”. The other arm extends to point and wave, and they switch places and repeat. This dance of alternating movement and stillness has the logic of dialog. The figures seem to respond to each other, pausing as if to listen or observe. Although they have no discernable means of sensing the world, they point at each other with a delicate accuracy that suggests awareness.</p>
<p>A key milestone in the development of infant consciousness occurs around nine months after birth. The infant at this age begins to follow the gaze of another and to direct the other’s attention by pointing at objects of interest.<sup><a href="#pointing">6</a></sup> One early study of the phenomenon seats an infant and an adult across from each other, then has the adult turn and point to the side with a theatrical “Oh, look!”<sup><a href="#joint-attention-study">7</a></sup> The researchers observe when and how the infant follows the adult’s gaze.<sup><a href="#following-gaze">8</a></sup> Some psychologists consider this joint attention sharing to be the child’s first demonstration of an awareness of the other as an intentional being like the self.<sup><a href="#joint-attention">9</a></sup> <em>Again</em> has a single outward-pointing gesture (the only gesture that was not present in the original <em>Robot Dance</em>). In this move, both figures point crookedly in the same horizontal direction and wave gently. This action is the dancerly expression of joint attention sharing.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/again_joint_attention.jpg"></img>
</figure>
<p>Many of the motifs in <em>Again</em> are present in Rath’s earliest two-part robotic sculptures: <em>Robot Dance</em>, <em>Meet Me at the Corner</em>, and <em>One Track Minds</em>. It is in the spare forms and bipartite compositions of these works that Rath first identifies a formal language adequate to the exploration of the relationship between self and other. In these works, as in <em>Again</em>, there is so little to see that every gesture acquires unmerited significance. The extreme simplicity of these pieces allows them to transcend the details of any particular self and other to depict the ideas in the abstract. The larger and more varied ensembles, like <em>Friends and Acquaintances</em>, <em>Pair</em>, and <em>Five on a Wall</em> fail to achieve the same presence – although they do elicit a certain prurient fascination. Though the repertoire of movements is simple, the machines themselves are a wild menagerie of colors, textures, and forms, different in almost every way from each other. The interplay of commonality and difference that constitutes the presence of self and other is subsumed under a welter of visual details.</p>
<p>Two questions remain: If <em>Robot Dance</em> contains the essential elements of the later work, why did Rath bother with <em>Again</em> at all? And why should we? Perhaps because <em>Again</em> visibly improves on <em>Robot Dance</em> in many small ways. The black plywood armature focuses attention on the choreography by heightening the contrast with the wall and by concealing the electronics. The movements themselves are smoother and more expressive. In <em>Robot Dance</em>, each figure moves segment-by-segment; in <em>Again</em>, the entire arm moves at once in a single fluid motion. The smallest segment, limited to 120 degrees of rotation in <em>Robot Dance</em>, is free to spin full circle in <em>Again</em>, which it does with a spirit of gleeful abandon. Yet these details alone don’t seem to justify <em>Again</em>, nor do they explain why Rath returned to <em>Robot Dance</em> after twenty years of exploring other forms.</p>
<p>The answer to these questions is hidden in the story of <em>Again</em>’s electronics. All of the electrical components in <em>Again</em> are custom-made. This custom hardware by its design makes the themes of the choreography an integral part of the sculpture. It was only in 2015, when Rath began working on <em>Again</em>, that it was possible for him to give <em>Again</em> this deep thematic consistency. But the story of <em>Again</em>’s electronics begins much earlier.</p>
<p>The idea for a machine with dancing arms first occurred to Rath in childhood. <em>Robot Dance</em> was the first realization of that idea, and it is best understood as a sketch, a prototype that was ahead of its time. Rath built <em>Robot Dance</em> as soon as he could buy a computer powerful enough to calculate its trajectories. <em>Robot Dance</em> was clumsy, but it acted as a signpost: it showed Rath what he had to learn in order to fully realize his idea. Over the next twenty years, Rath developed the skills, tools, and electrical components demanded by his vision of a graceful, self-sufficient <em>Robot Dance</em>. <em>Meet Me at the Corner</em> features Rath’s first custom-built belt-and-pulley system. Immediately afterwards, Rath bought a mill and a lathe, machine tools more powerful than his earlier drill press. For the solitary feathered sculptures that Rath started making in the 2000s, he developed custom motor controllers, powerful and light, each with a built-in microcontroller for planning movement and communicating over the network. <em>Again</em> combines all of these inventions. <em>Again</em> is built entirely from Rath’s own custom-made components. The custom components smooth the movements, a small change that makes a big difference in the quality of the anthropomorphic illusion. Each electronic component in <em>Again</em> has just the strength it needs, and no more. The components were designed for each other, and they fit together perfectly to create a irreducible whole. Where <em>Robot Dance</em> had to be clumsily assembled piece-by-piece for each installation, <em>Again</em> is self-contained. In this way, the hardware reflects the same tension between interdependence and autonomy that characterizes the choreography.</p>
<p>I said the best place to view <em>Again</em> is from fifteen feet back. It is possible also to come close to <em>Again</em> and to stand so that the pulley belts and red electrical wires inside the arm are visible. At this distance, consciousness disappears, and the work appears entirely mechanical. It is easy to resume the illusion of consciousness (just step backwards), but impossible to hold both impressions in mind at the same time. This experience of walking around <em>Again</em> demonstrates how personal is the judgment of an other’s consciousness. Originating as it does in subjective, first-person experience, it is possible that consciousness will always be fundamentally beyond the reach of science. Yet it is clear that we need a science of consciousness. Left alone, our judgments of consciousness are too much guided by convenience: we anthropomorphize our pets and convince ourselves of the mindlessness of the cows and chicken whose flesh fills our plates. A complete philosophy of consciousness must embrace both the scientific and the subjective. Until such a philosophy is devised, <em>Again</em> will serve as a rare reminder of the way that these two modes of knowing are tangled in the experience of self and other.</p>
<hr />
<p class="text-secondary">
Thanks to Abigail Kelly, Amantia Muhedini, and Mike Webb for commenting on drafts of this essay.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
This essay originally appeared in the catalog <a href="https://hosfelt-gallery.square.site/product/alan-rath-virtual-unreality-catalog/7"><em>Alan Rath: Virtual Unreality</em></a>, published by the <a href="https://www.icasanjose.org">San Jose Institute of Contemporary Art</a> and <a href="http://hosfeltgallery.com">Hosfelt Gallery</a> on the occasion of the retrospective <a href="https://www.icasanjose.org/archive/virtual-unreality">exhibition</a> of the same name.
</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes</h5>
<div class="footnotes">
<p><a name="subjective-experience">1.</a> Philosophers Thomas Nagel and John Searle exemplify this tradition in the philosophy of mind. See Nagel, “What is it like to be a bat?” and Searle, “Reductionism and the Irreducibility of Consciousness” in <em>Emergence: Contemporary Readings in Philosophy and Science</em>, ed. Mark A. Bedau and Paul Humphreys (2008).</p>
<p><a name="dennett">2.</a> Dennett, <em>The Intentional Stance</em> (1987) and <em>Consciousness Explained</em> (1991). For a wonderful overview of Dennett’s approach to consciousness, see the short essay “Real Patterns,” in <em>Emergence: Contemporary Readings in Philosophy and Science</em>, ed. Mark A. Bedau and Paul Humphreys (2008).</p>
<p><a name="mimicking-facial-expressions">3.</a> The original publication is “Newborn Infants Imitate Adult Facial Gestures,” by Meltzoff &amp; Moore (1983). See “The role of imitation in understanding persons and developing a theory of mind,” by Meltzoff &amp; Gopnik (1993) for an overview of the confirming studies which followed this initial experiment.</p>
<p><a name="full-awareness">4.</a> Tomasello, <em>The Cultural Origins of Human Cognition</em> (1999), p. 174.</p>
<p><a name="cognitive-labor-symmetry">5.</a> For an interesting discussion of studies in the mental labor of observing symmetries, see Daniel Dennett, “Towards a Cognitive Theory of Consciousness”, pp. 219 - 221.</p>
<p><a name="pointing">6.</a> Tomasello, “Joint Attention as Social Cognition” in <em>Joint Attention: Its Origin and Role in Development</em>, ed. Chris Moore and Philip J. Dunham (2016), pp. 103 - 105.</p>
<p><a name="joint-attention-study">7.</a> Jerome Bruner. “From Joint Attention to the Meeting of Minds: An Introduction” in <em>Joint Attention: Its Origin and Role in Development</em>, ed. Chris Moore and Philip J. Dunham (2016), p. 7.</p>
<p><a name="following-gaze">8.</a> Scaife, Michael and Jerome Bruner. “The capacity for joint visual attention in the infant,”
Nature, volume 253, pp. 265–266 (24 January 1975).</p>
<p><a name="joint-attention">9.</a> Tomasello, <em>The Cultural Origins of Human Cognition</em>, pp. 62 - 70.</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Skepticism and Despair in <i>The Infinity Engine</i></title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/infinity-engine/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/infinity-engine/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-05-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <em>The Infinity Engine</em> (2014 - 2017), artist Lynn Hershman Leeson offers a concentrated experience of the contemporary debate over the implications of genetic modification and other emerging biotechnologies. The multimedia installation traces the movement of these technologies through society from inception in the laboratory to eventual acceptance into living human bodies. For me, a layperson, the <em>The Infinity Engine</em> awakens a disheartening awareness of the uncertainty of our biological future and my own lack of agency.</p>
<p>Visitors enter <em>The Infinity Engine</em> through a two-channel video installation depicting a bioengineering laboratory. The video evokes in me a complex and contradictory emotional response: curiosity and frustration, suspicion and guilt. One channel shows a drab, dimly lit hallway blocked at the end by a pair of closed doors. Over the slow course of several minutes, the camera approaches the end of the hallway, rebounds, and retreats backwards, always keeping the closed doors in view. The long sojourn in the empty hallway, combined with the tantalizing glimpses beyond the door are a cinematic shell game, an obvious ploy that nonetheless makes me feel both curious and excluded.</p>
<p>Next to the projection of the empty hallway, a second video channel shows the laboratory itself, a cluttered maze populated by scientists in white lab coats. Admittance to the inner sanctum piques my curiosity, but also, paradoxically, makes me feel more excluded. The camera, held at waist level, makes me feel like a child lost in the laboratory. The space is full of machines that look like sophisticated dishwashers and refrigerators and boilers as well as inscrutable countertop appliances that tremble and twirl. A dramatic close-up of a fleshy triangular object — a bioengineered nose — reveals the ultimate product of the scientists’ efforts. The purposeful movements suggest a complex coordination that is hidden from view. Yet we are ostentatiously excluded from understanding the way that the activities of the scientists converge to produce this miracle. The video is silent, and the faces of the scientists are rendered unreadable by deep shadows added in post-production.</p>
<p>I can hardly disclose my foiled curiosity without also mentioning the dreadful suspense I feel as I watch the video. The inescapable gloom of the long hallway, the blue-green tint of the laboratory, and the faceless people in white robes all contribute to this sense of foreboding. It is a mark of our times (or perhaps merely of my acculturation into the enthusiastic technoculture of the Bay Area) that I feel guilty at my unease. I feel that I am doubting the beneficence of science, assenting to a nebulous anti-scientific skepticism. And how different, I wonder, is this skepticism from the much-ridiculed skepticism of the anti-vaccer or creationist?</p>
<p>Passing through the video installation into the main room of <em>The Infinity Engine</em>, I’m surprised at the persistence with which the installation is grounded in the ethical uncertainties and constraints of the present. Hershman Leeson muses in an interview about <em>The Infinity Engine</em>, “you have have designer babies…and in a sense that’s’ biological censorship…there’s one company that can erase part of your memory…if they can erase memories, maybe they can put in memories.” Yet in the installation itself, she eschews the vivid dystopias of <em>Brave New World</em> and the more recent <em>Black Mirror</em>. Instead, <em>The Infinity Engine</em> juxtaposes the concrete benefits already afforded by emerging biotechnologies with contemporary struggles over access, control, and ownership.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/wallpaper.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
The wallpaper in the installation displays a seemingly <em>infinite</em> array of recent biotechnological discoveries and inventions. These advances are juxtaposed against images of their laboratory origins.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The emotional intensity of <em>The Infinity Engine</em> comes from the sincerity of Hershman Leeson’s engagement with scientists and cynics alike, as well as her characteristic use of irony. The iconic wallpaper catalogs bioengineered crops and farm animals, each captioned with the motivation for their development: “Increase milk production” — “Reduce the population of the dengue fever based mosquito” — “Resistance to slugs.” Interviews with biologist Elizabeth Blackburn show the Nobel laureate still shining with quiet excitement as she relates the details of her 1984 co-discovery of telomerase. I was genuinely inspired by a promotional video for regenerative medicine, produced by Hershman Leeson, in which Luke Masala, a healthy 19 year-old boy mowing the lawn shirtless in the summer heat, reveals that he was given an artificial bladder grown from his own cells when he was 9 years old. Elsewhere, in reports from the OECD, FDA and WHO with titles like “<a href="http://www.oecd.org/science/biotrack/1958527.pdf">Safety Considerations for Biotechnology</a>” and “<a href="https://www.aphis.usda.gov/brs/fedregister/coordinated_framework.pdf">Coordinated Framework for Regulation of Biotechnology</a>,” and in interviews with sociologist Troy Duster and artist Oron Catts, the installation gives voice to earnest criticisms and proposed solutions for the problems of biotechnology.</p>
<p>Yet always, the struggle to harness the potential of biotechnology is dominated by experts: scientists and engineers, economists and judges, all of whose activity is made to seem incomprehensible. In the video of the laboratory, the scientists’ movements are emptied of meaning by silence, fragmentation, and by careful framing that keeps the material transformations of chemicals into living tissue hidden just out of sight. In the next room a tongue-in-cheek invitation — “Visitors are welcome to read through the patent infringement cases” — belies the overwhelming prospect of hundreds of pages of patent filings, Supreme Court opinions, and technical reports, labeled clearly, but unordered and without any explanation. The only amateur response to biotechnology modeled by the installation is Luke Masala’s uncritical “woooow!” Likewise, the aestheticized 3D-printed ear and tank of genetically modified fish offer visitors an opportunity to practice passive, uncomprehending amazement, but little else.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/documents.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Two boxes hold hundreds of pages of technical reports, patents filings, Supreme Court opinions, and policy recommendations related to biotechnology.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Irony and sincerity jostle against each other in <em>The Infinity Engine</em>. Hershman Leeson has long used irony in her work. In her 1975 <em><a href="http://www.bitforms.com/leeson/roberta-construction-chart-2">Roberta Breitmore Construction Chart</a></em>, Hershman Leeson annotates a photographic portrait of her eponymous alter-ego with “suggested alterations”: “reshape lips” and “add: false eyelashes.” The satisfying bite of the <em>Construction Chart</em> comes from the sharp contradiction between the cosmetic instructions and their intended interpretation. In <em>The Infinity Engine</em>, a science fair poster situates contemporary “biomaterials” in a historical lineage of medical intervention beginning with ancient Egyptian wooden prosthetics — earnestly illustrated with a grotesque photograph of a desiccated, mummified foot. Another poster advertising an experimental regenerative medicine program for ‘Wounded Warriors’ leaves untouched the senseless violence of war itself. By far the most dramatic ironic gesture is the floor-to-ceiling riff on <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Creation_of_Adam">The Creation of Adam</a></em>, reinterpreted for the laboratory with gloved hands and syringes. This brazen, kitschy image touches at once the opposition of religious groups to genetic modification, the hubris of scientists — and, more subtly, suggests that, left alone, scientists will create the future in their own image.</p>
<p>I leave <em>The Infinity Engine</em> the way I came, past the eerie video installation. On my way out, I catch sight of myself in the floor-to-ceiling mirrors opposite the projection, where it looks like I, too, am walking purposefully through the laboratory. Feeling uncertain and helpless, I wonder again where I fit into the laboratory and its bioengineered future. Perhaps the resignation of <em>The Infinity Engine</em> would be a comfortable relief. Yet somehow, against this “laugh that leaves one with no breath at all,”<sup><a href="#sontag">1</a></sup> I am determined to cling to the possibility of ethical action in the face of scientific progress.</p>
<hr />
<h5 id="notes">Notes</h5>
<div class="footnotes">
<p><a name="sontag">1.</a> Sontag, Susan. “The Aesthetics of Solitude” in <em>Studies of Radical Will</em>. New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1969.</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Surface Tension</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/camille-utterback-sustaining-presence/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/camille-utterback-sustaining-presence/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-03-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Winston Churchill once said, “We make our buildings and afterwards they make us.” The same is true of technology. Linear perspective,<sup><a href="#rationalization-of-sight">1</a></sup> the printing press,<sup><a href="#printing-press">2</a></sup> the camera,<sup><a href="#on-photography">3</a></sup> the computer;<sup><a href="#second-self">4</a></sup> these technologies have changed irreversibly the way the world appears to us, how we relate to each other, and the way we see ourselves. Digital display technology is poised now to effect a similar transformation in the way that we see the world. Already ubiquitous on cellphone screens, digital images will become increasingly inseparable from physical reality with the spread of augmented and virtual reality technologies. In her <a href="http://events.stanford.edu/events/635/63511/">show of digital installation art</a> at the Stanford Art Gallery, artist Camille Utterback offers a critique of the digital screen and a hopeful exploration of the possibilities of an augmented reality which is deeply based in the physical world.</p>
<p>The digital screen aspires to be both universal and invisible, a transparent window onto the world. In the conference room and classroom, smooth white projection screens roll down from the ceiling; on laptops and cellphones, retina displays and anti-glare film and vanishing bezels suppress the material presence of the screen. Limited in its early days by low resolution and color depth, the contemporary screen claims to contain all images: pornography as well as piety, gore as well as graphs. Utterback’s glass projection sculptures in <em>Sustaining Presence</em> dismantle the false neutrality of the digital screen and expand the possible meanings of the digital image.</p>
<p>In fact, transparency has become (or always was) essential to the definition of the digital screen.
<em>Radiant Cache</em> presents video footage of trees is projected into thick glass tablets - rectangular, like most screens the world over. The projected images are hazy and punctuated by ghostly bubbles and impurities beneath the surface of the glass. In one tablet, a charcoal-dark cloud inside the tablet nearly extinguishes the moving image. This dark blot reads clearly as an interruption of the screen. Other impurities are puddles of frosted white glass which focus and sharpen the projected video. The consistency of movement across the tablet indicates that the entire video is captured from the same scene. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_law_of_thermodynamics">folk wisdom that order gives way to disorder (but rarely the other way round)</a> identifies the most precise patches of the image as those which are most faithful to the original scene. The fragments of frosted glass appear as the source of truth, the real window onto the subject of the image; in other words, the screen. The body of the tablet, conversely, is demoted to a mere backdrop, caught in limbo between screen and non-screen.</p>
<p><em>Light Field</em> further undermines the transparency of the screen by highlighting the two-dimensionality of the projection surface. The title of this piece puns on the double meaning of “field” as both the flat, grassy habitat shown in the video footage, and, in physics, as a physical quantity present at all points in space (like the electromagnetic field, which gives rise to light). Visible from all sides, <em>Light Field</em> dissolves the illusion of the screen as a window. The slivered screens seem almost to offer slices of space and time carved out of another world and suspended in glass. Yet the video shows a head-on landscape view of the field, not a sectional cut through it. The rhythmic swaying of grass and wildflowers moving laterally across the screens traces the flat surface of the picture plane. In one glass orb, the projected footage follows the curving wisp of opaque glass through a smooth 180° turn. Paradoxically, the dramatic three-dimensionality of this screen heightens the apparent flatness of the projected image. Critic Clement Greenberg in 1961 framed a history of Modernist painting around the discovery of flatness as the defining quality of the medium.<sup><a href="#modernist-painting">5</a></sup> New media raise new questions. Today, the rapid proliferation of new kinds of illusionistic, three-dimensional depictions in augmented and virtual reality resurrect the question of flatness.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4ctr_-X9f5w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>In <em>Radiant Cache</em> and <em>Holding Water</em>, the overlap between the visual forms of image and screen challenges the supposed universality of the screen. In <em>Radiant Cache</em>, footage of trees is projected into thick glass tablets - rectangular, like most screens the world over. But the projected images are hazy and punctuated by ghostly bubbles and impurities beneath the surface of the glass. Sometimes, it’s hard to tell if regularities in the moving image come from the video, or the screen. In one tablet, charcoal-dark smudges in the glass which seem to extinguish the moving image masquerade as shadowed tree trunks. The videos appear clearly only in the small patches of each tablet where opaque frosted glass focuses the projected light. Closely-spaced stripes of opaque glass in one tablet seem to reveal the image of a palm leaf swaying in the wind. Yet, on close inspection, it’s hard to separate the fringe of the palm leaf in the video from the glass fringe under the surface of the screen. Video and screen blur and become entangled. Screen and video are uniquely suited to each other; separately, they would be diminished.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/KzsXMJo8fQY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>In <em>Holding Water</em>, oversize glass drinking vessels with frosted cups serve as screens for video footage of water projected from above. The functional associations of these drinking vessels reinforce the projected illusion of water, only to be undermined by the <a href="https://youtu.be/zaeKG8aRdZ8">waterstriders and twigs skimming the surface</a>. The videos fill the bottoms of the cups evenly, like real water, conjuring a “surface” where the projection ends. Between this imaginary riparian surface and the bottom of the cup is a space which could not exist on a classroom projection screen - the volume of the improbable virtual water itself. The piece offers yet another contradiction in the rightmost vessel, which is tilted so that the surface of the projected water hangs improbably at an angle, defying the physics which make the other projections so convincing. This pulling-apart reveals the latent tension between the presumed universality of the screen and the specificity of the image. This tension will find its resolution in augmented reality, where image and screen can fuse together in an inseparable media symbiosis.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fqei6pjqbns" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>Beyond the play of light and the movement of waves which constitute the illusion of water, the videos in <em>Holding Water</em> are dominated by shadows and reflected colors. The blue aura which recalls the glow of a computer screen in a dark room is surely that of the sky. In the tallest vessel, a yellowish-green gradient suggests trees leaning over the river, as do dark forms poking into the leftmost cup. The central goblet is filled with the trembling reflections of rushes swaying in the wind. The surface of the water is both a projected illusion in the gallery and, in nature, a screen for the reflected images of grass and trees. This duality is both a critique, and a comfort. Through the double distance of reflection and projection, <em>Holding Water</em> creates a self-conscious augmented reality which contains its own critique. Yet, in the analogy between natural reflection and artificial projection, <em>Holding Water</em> also reminds us that representational illusion long precedes augmented reality, and that it is a fundamental feature of the way we inhabit and interpret the world.</p>
<p>Marshall McLuhan writes that, “the “message” of any medium or technology is the change of scale or pace or pattern that it introduces into human affairs.”<sup><a href="#medium-is-the-message">6</a></sup> Augmented reality is here to stay; projects like <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/microsoft-hololens/en-us">Hololens</a>, <a href="https://www.magicleap.com/#/home">Magic Leap</a>, and <a href="https://www.oculus.com/rift/">Oculus Rift</a> will make sure of that. It remains to be seen what change of pattern or scale augmented reality will bring. In the words of anthropologist Sherry Turkle: “what remains timely is finding ways to work with simulation yet be accountable to nature.”<sup><a href="#simulation-and-its-discontents">7</a></sup> In <em>Sustaining Presence</em>, Utterback has given us a good start.</p>
<hr />
<p class="text-secondary">
Thanks to <a href="https://abbylapier.com/">Abby LaPier</a> for a wonderfully productive conversation which suggested many of the ideas in this piece.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
For further reading on these topics, see my <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1RQjTmWoGaPzDGnQMYfEyynjl8Ou-dWl3FB_g39f2WvE/pub">full list of sources</a>.
</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes</h5>
<div class="footnotes">
<p><a name="rationalization-of-sight">1.</a> William Ivins, <a href="http://www.metmuseum.org/art/metpublications/Papers_On_the_Rationalization_of_Sight"><em>On the Rationalization of Sight</em></a> (1938).</p>
<p><a name="printing-press">2.</a> Elizabeth Eisenstein, <em>The Printing Press as an Agent of Change</em> (1979).</p>
<p><a name="on-photography">3.</a> Susan Sontag, <em>On Photography</em> (1977).</p>
<p><a name="second-self">4.</a> Sherry Turkle, <em>The Second Self: Computers and the Human Spirit</em> (1984).</p>
<p><a name="modernist-painting">5.</a> Clement Greenberg, <em>Modernist Painting</em> (1960).</p>
<p><a name="medium-is-the-message">6.</a> Marshall McLuhan, “The Medium is the Message,” in <em>Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man</em> (1964).</p>
<p><a name="simulation-and-its-discontents">7.</a> Sherry Turkle, <em>Simulation and Its Discontents</em> (2009), 45.</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>I Have No Memory of This Place</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/sohei-nishino-new-work/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/sohei-nishino-new-work/index.html</id>
    <published>2017-01-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I first saw <a href="http://soheinishino.net/">Sohei Nishino</a>’s map of San Francisco at SFMOMA, I felt an inexplicable, irrational sense of resentment. Behind me, a teenager crowed to his friends: “I don’t even have to look at the label, I can tell that one is San Francisco.” Nishino’s map of San Francisco is instantly recognizable from a distance, but as I inspected its details, I felt indignant in spite of myself. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bSrf8EgSyDg">Nishino’s city wasn’t the San Francisco that I knew</a>. Missing were the familiar sights that dominate my memories of the city: Mission Street’s shabby bodegas and dollar stores; the bookshops and taquerias fronting on narrow, shaded sidewalks along 24th Street; the cliffs of Thornton State Beach, draped with spiky succulent sea fig.</p>
<p>Nishino’s <a href="http://soheinishino.net/dioramamap/">Diorama Maps</a> combine mapping and photography, two of our most powerful technologies for producing truths about places beyond our immediate experience. In recent decades, scholarship in critical cartography and widespread awareness of digital manipulation in photography have revealed each medium as purposeful and duplicitous. Yet this knowledge has done little to shake our faith in the truthfulness of either medium. Nishino’s show of cartographic photocollages <a href="https://www.sfmoma.org/exhibition/new-work-sohei-nishino/">now on view at SFMOMA</a> explores the ease with which maps and photographs so often appear under the guise of truth. The two mediums are joined in Nishino’s work by an insight from cognitive psychology. Decades of research in the psychology of spatial perception have shown that maps, photographs, and lived experience linger and accumulate in the mind to form spatial mental models called cognitive maps. In his photocollages, Nishino uses cartography and photography to visualize his own cognitive maps. By combining these familiar media in pursuit of the internal and intangible cognitive map, Nishino sheds new light on the apparent truthfulness of maps and photographs.</p>
<p>Each of the artist’s Diorama Maps depicts a single city through thousands of his own photographs. Nishino wanders through the city on foot, snapping pictures from sidewalks and rooftops with a film camera. He uses every single photograph in the resulting collage, cutting and pasting contact prints to construct an expansive and personal image of the city. Nishino explained in a <a href="https://www.sfmoma.org/watch/sohei-nishinos-maps-trace-more-city/">2016 interview</a>, “I create [my maps] based on my individual experiences and observations…everyone has a map of certain cities in their minds, depending on their experiences. That’s what I’m trying to capture.”</p>
<p>The notion that everyone has “a map of certain cities in their mind” was first systematically explored in the 1950s by urban planner Kevin Lynch. Using the tools of the psychologist, rather than the artist, Lynch and his collaborators interviewed dozens of city dwellers, asking them to sketch maps from memory or give instructions for traveling between two familiar places. Lynch synthesized the results of these surveys in schematic diagrams (below). These diagrams are tantalizing: they suggest that the accumulated experience of the city might be summarized and grasped at a glance. Lynch wrote that, “It was as if the map were drawn on an infinitely flexible rubber sheet; directions were twisted, distances stretched or compressed, large forms so changed from their accurate scale projection as to be at first unrecognizable…[but] the map was rarely torn and sewn back together in another order.”<sup><a href="#image-of-the-city">1</a></sup> Lynch’s diagrams are remarkable in the way that they materialize mental maps, but are also narrow, inflexible, and purposefully stripped of emotional depth in favor of abstraction. Nishino’s procedure provides a new model for visualizing cognitive maps which is evocative and open-ended.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/lynch-diagram-boston-verbal.jpg"></img>
<img src="./images/lynch-diagram-boston-sketch.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Lynch’s diagrams of Boston show the city as derived from verbal interviews and sketch maps. Each method produces a subtly different representation of the cognitive map. These differences caution against interpreting any representation as a completely transparent image of a cognitive map.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Nishino’s maps recall their cognitive counterparts in their deviations from textbook geography. Each Diorama Map is partial, fragmentary, and distorted. As in Lynch’s “rubber sheet” diagrams, landmarks, roads, and natural features are magnified, duplicated, misplaced, or omitted entirely. In Nishino’s map of San Francisco, Golden Gate Park and the Presidio are vastly enlarged, swollen with frisbee players and intrepid bathers, while the entire Southern half of the city is squeezed into a sliver at the bottom. The famous Victorian Painted Ladies match City Hall in height, and Twin Peaks appears twice, from different perspectives, as befits a landmark visible throughout the city. Each of these images is individually lifelike and credible. The distortions and omissions in the map arise from relationships between photographs. Indeed, the map is nothing more than a gestalt which emerges from the patterns of light and dark in the assembled images. The photographs wholly constitute the map. This extreme intimacy of map and photograph is novel, and it dramatizes the differences between the truth claims of each medium.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/twin-peaks-from-afar.jpg"></img>
</figure>
<figure>
<img src="./images/twin-peaks-up-close.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Twin Peaks appears twice in Nishino’s map of San Francisco. Images courtesy of <a href="http://www.michaelhoppengallery.com/artists/25-sohei-nishino/overview/">Michael Hoppen Gallery</a>. ‘Diorama Map San Francisco, 2016’, © Sohei Nishino
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Susan Sontag wrote that, “photographed images do not seem to be statements about the world so much as pieces of it, miniatures of reality.”<sup><a href="#on-photography">2</a></sup> Historian of film Tom Gunning described this quality as photography’s truth claim. Gunning argued that the credibility of photographs as “miniatures of reality” arises from their unrivaled visual accuracy and their construction as the causal end-product of a deterministic physical process<sup><a href="#gunning">3</a></sup>. That is, Gunning argued that our scientific knowledge of the interaction between light and photographic chemicals endows the photograph with the appearance of objectivity. Nishino’s Diorama Maps extend Gunning’s argument by emphasizing that photographs claim a particular kind of truth: every photograph announces a personal, past experience. A painting or drawing may be inspired by past events, but it has no necessary connection to the past; the painter is free to show the never-was and the yet-to-be. Photographs are different. Our knowledge of the causal relationship between the photograph and the event it depicts marks the photograph as a representation of a past moment. Photographs are also distinctive for their mimicry of human visual perception. Produced by lenses which recall those in the human eye, photographs capture many of the essential features of human vision, like linear perspective. These qualities, familiar from our own visual experience, cue us to recognize the photograph as a representation of another person’s experience. In this way, photographs are always personal.</p>
<p>Maps, by contrast, claim universal truths. Where photographs invite empathetic identification, map projections show the world from a disembodied bird’s-eye. Divorced and abstracted from any corporeal vantage point or particular past time, the map seems unbound from particular human experiences. The impersonal map announces its contents to all viewers indiscriminately (it is precisely the universal quality of maps that give rise to disputes like <a href="http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Data_working_group/Disputes#Jerusalem_Name_Dispute">this one on OpenStreetMap about whether Jerusalem should be labeled ירושלים or القدس</a>). Further, maps derive authority from their usage in everyday life. We use maps to figure out when to leave or stay, where to go, and how to get there. There are other kinds of maps - historical, statistical, fantastic - but it is as navigation aids that maps are most widely and actively used. Unlike a photograph, which intrinsically represents the past, the map-as-navigation-aid is a promise about a place which anticipates future action. Such maps are useful only insofar as they correspond to the physical world they represent, and each map-aided journey completes a feedback loop which confirms the map as a truthful form by testing it against the real world.</p>
<p>By organizing his photographs in the shape of a map (or, alternatively, by populating each map with photographs), Nishino establishes a tension between the truth claims of these different mediums. The photographs personalize the map, making it a record of Nishino’s unique experience. At the same time, the map universalizes Nishino’s photographs so that each photograph appears as the truth of a particular place.</p>
<p>Standing in SFMOMA, it’s the overreaching photos, not the distorted maps, which I resent in Nishino’s Diorama Map of San Francisco. After all, we seldom have direct experience of the shapes of our cities. What’s more, cartographic distortions are commonplace in <a href="http://benschmidt.org/mta/">subway maps</a> and in <a href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mejn/election/2016/">statistical maps</a>, which claim to be all the more truthful as a result. Each photograph in a Diorama Map is bound by its cartographic context to fulfill the map’s promise of agnostic, reproducible truths about places. Yet this is an impossible task for a medium which is personal, fleeting, and fixed to the past.</p>
<p>We expect our cognitive maps to serve as truthful representations and reliable guides. Yet, because they are immaterial, made of nothing more than memories and sense impressions, they go uninspected; we seldom notice their gaps, omissions, and distortions. Someday, perhaps, technology could allow each of us to visualize our own cognitive map in a Sohei Nishino-style collage. Until then, Nishino’s maps will remind us to cultivate a healthy skepticism for spatial representation and to broaden our experience of the city by seeking the unknown: walking and biking to new neighborhoods, attending thoughtfully to details in the environment, and traveling unaccustomed paths.</p>
<hr />
<p class="text-secondary">
Thanks to Abigail Kelly for reading this piece and giving wonderful, helpful feedback.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
For further reading, see my <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OIoKdH-Z5EmVdo3zMJfooF5qHxbYIHE2fYtyHGOWfIg/pub">full list of sources</a>.
</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes</h5>
<div class="footnotes">
<p><a name="image-of-the-city">1.</a> Lynch, Kevin. <em>The Image of the City</em>. 87.</p>
<p><a name="on-photography">2.</a> Sontag, Susan. <em>On Photography</em>. London: Penguin, 1977.</p>
<p><a name="gunning">3.</a> Gunning, Tom. “What’s the Point of an Index? Or, Faking Photographs.” Still Moving (2008): 40.</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Culture and Spatial Perception in the Art of teamLab</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/teamLab-living-digital-space-future-parks/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/teamLab-living-digital-space-future-parks/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-10T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The best visual spectacle in the Bay Area right now is the show of digital installation art by Japanese art group <a href="http://www.team-lab.net/">teamLab</a> at <a href="http://www.pacegallery.com/">Pace Art + Technology</a> in Menlo Park. The show is a vast warren of dazzling sights: a <a href="http://exhibition.team-lab.net/siliconvalley/art/art01.html">narrow path through a forest of glowing LEDs</a>, a <a href="http://exhibition.team-lab.net/siliconvalley/art/art09.html">cave full of projected flowers endlessly blooming and dying</a>, a <a href="http://exhibition.team-lab.net/siliconvalley/art/art02.html">hazy world of dark waves stretching into infinity</a>. The twenty artworks are beautiful, intricate, and masterfully executed, but they quickly blur together into a highbrow funhouse, a sophisticated trade show. The show is grounded in teamLab’s homegrown theory of spatial perception and motivated by the group’s ambitions for social harmony and the advancement of Japanese art. These ideas might have elevated the show, but they are underdeveloped and unconvincing. Nevertheless, they suggest exciting new directions for inquiry into the relationship between culture and perception.</p>
<p>The show is anchored by a theory of spatial perception which teamLab calls <a href="https://www.team-lab.net/concept/chou_shukan_kukan/">Ultra Subjective Space</a>. This theory is teamLab’s challenge to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perspective_(graphical)">linear perspective</a>, the system of spatial representation developed during the Italian Renaissance. In linear perspective, objects which are farther away from the viewer appear smaller, while Ultra Subjective Space shares with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_projection">parallel projection</a> the tendency for objects to climb vertically as they recede, without diminishing in size. Perspective originated as a geometric specification for representing space and shaped subsequent Western artistic output through its force as an idea. Against this, teamLab developed Ultra Subjective Space by looking backwards. Beginning with the assumption that Japanese painting must have been silently guided by a system of spatial representation analogous to linear perspective, the group set out to uncover this hidden set of laws by recreating traditional Japanese paintings using digital modeling and rendering.</p>
<p>teamLab is hardly the first group to think beyond linear perspective. Subverting linear perspective is by now a tradition almost as venerable as perspective itself. More than a hundred years ago, Cubism and other Modern movements broke the centuries-long hegemony of linear perspective over fine art in the West with paintings and manifestos exploring multiple vantage points. Yet today, perspective still dominates popular art through photography, film, animation, and illustration, and it maintains an exclusive claim on truth that other modes of spatial representation have been unable to match. For most Western viewers, perspectival spatial recognition is a reflexive habit, and familiarity blinds us to its pervasive presence, making it hard to adopt or even imagine alternatives.</p>
<p>Though the crusade against linear perspective is not new, teamLab’s motivation for pursuing it is unique, forged from a combined belief in the power of Ultra Subjective Space to foster social harmony and advance the international appreciation of Japan’s classical cultural heritage. Toshiyuki Inoko, the founder of teamLab, mused in a <a href="http://ultrasubjectivespace.com/">2013 interview</a>: “What if a visual approach different from Western spatial recognition took root and became the norm? If all of mankind were looking at the world in that spatial manner [of Ultra Subjective Space], before long the boundaries between man and his environment would stop making sense, and we might create a new kind of society and culture.” The mission of the show, then, is to make Ultra Subjective Space intelligible, palatable, and even natural.</p>
<p>Sadly, I found the earnest texts accompanying the artworks in the Menlo Park exhibition to be utterly unconvincing, full of ambitious unsupported claims which didn’t match my experience of linear perspective or of teamLab’s artworks. teamLab says that in Ultra Subjective Space, there is, “no barrier between the viewer and the projection surface,” and that viewers can, “can pretend to enter and move around freely within the space of the painting…without priority over anybody else.” Although Ultra Subjective Space is presented as an analogue of linear perspective, it is never precisely defined, either in terms of teamLab’s computer models or by reference to classical Japanese writing on aesthetics. Because the mechanics of Ultra Subjective Space are never specified, it’s impossible to assess the truth of teamLab’s claims, except through experience. Likewise, the supposed utopian effects of Ultra Subjective Space are so broad as to be meaningless (What kind of new society and culture might Ultra Subjective Space create? How would it change the relationships between people and nature?) In the absence of compelling verbal arguments for Ultra Subjective Space, the task of persuasion is left to the artworks themselves.</p>
<p><em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em>, a lush animated narrative which unfolds simultaneously across twelve digital screens, demonstrates the three-dimensionality of Ultra Subjective Space. Modeled after paintings like the 17th century <em>rakuchū rakugai zu</em> (<em>Scenes in and around the Capital</em>), and <em>Tale of Genji</em>, <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> is unmistakably Japanese in style, an exemplar of Ultra Subjective Space. As the camera orbits through the depicted scene, the landscape changes smoothly, reassuring the viewer that this space, though it appears flat, has volume and depth enough to accommodate movement and multiple points of view. The animated images in <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> play on repeat, and shortly into each loop, the surface of the image begins to flake away to reveal a skeletal wireframe underneath. Drawn in the style of an engineering blueprint or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minkowski_diagram#/media/File:GPB_circling_earth.jpg">physics diagram</a>, this wireframe dramatizes the technological nature of the 3D digital model used to create the image. This wireframe is an abstracted representation of the world which is legible to Western viewers. It mediates between Japanese and Western forms of spatial recognition and lends the Japanese approach an aura of scientific credibility.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/rakuchu-rakugai-zu.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
The <em>rakuchū rakugai zu</em>, or <em>Scenes in and around the capital</em> was a popular subject in 17th century Japanese art. This rendition, painted on a pair of six-panel folding screens (<em>Set of 12</em>…) recalls <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> in the birds-eye view, the use of parallel perspective, and the treatment of clouds (rendered with gold leaf). © <a href="http://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/53428">The Metropolitan Museum of Art</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<img src="./images/tale-of-genji.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Genji, the protagonist of <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em>, is drawn from the 11th century novel <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Tale_of_Genji">The Tale of Genji</a></em>. This set of painted screens depicting scenes from the <em>Tale of Genji</em> are from the mid-16th / early-17th century. © <a href="http://www.metmuseum.org/art/collection/search/39665">The Metropolitan Museum of Art</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>For me, <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> conveys the mechanics of Ultra Subjective Space without evoking its utopian effects. teamLab argue that images using Ultra Subjective Space bring the viewer into harmony with nature by dissolving the boundaries between experiential and depicted space. Yet I find that entering the space of <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> is a struggle. I am still in thrall to linear perspective, and imagining myself convincingly in a scene means seeing it in perspective. I can easily paste myself like a paper doll onto the surface of <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em>, but actually placing myself within the image requires an imaginative twist to warp isotropic space into linear perspective around my avatar. I find the image intelligible but inhospitable.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hXLa4s3TnyY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>Recent findings from cultural psychology offer a means of reconciling my experience of <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> with teamLab’s claims about Ultra Subjective Space. Psychologists Sean Duffy, Shinobu Kitayama, and Hazel Markus observe distinct “Eastern” and “Western” styles of visual perception and propose that they are anchored in different conceptions of the self. In the West, they write, “the normative imperative…is to become independent from others and to discover and express one’s own unique attributes,”<sup><a href="#culture-and-the-self">1</a></sup> while in the East, “responsiveness to the concerns of social others, as well as the expectations of others, forms the basis for action.”<sup><a href="#culture-modes-of-seeing-55">2</a></sup> Simply by living in a particular culture, people acquire skills, values, and behaviors which reinforce the culturally dominant mode of being. Duffy, Kitayama, and Markus argue that visual perception is one such culturally contingent skill.</p>
<p>Visual perception reflects the different conceptions of the self through complementary strategies of focused and dispersed visual attention. Duffy and Kitayama write that, “in the focused attention strategy, individual objects and their focal features receive the vast majority of the cognitive resources of attention,” while in the dispersed attention strategy, “objects surrounding the attended object, or features of the object’s context receive considerable attention, at the cost of focal information about the individual objects.”<sup><a href="#cultural-modes-of-seeing-57">3</a></sup> Using controlled experiments like the framed line test, Kitayama et. al. have shown that Japanese subjects excel at tasks requiring dispersed attention, while American subjects perform better on tasks requiring focused attention.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/framed-line-test.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
In the framed line test (FLT), subjects are shown a line inside a frame (above, left), and then asked to reproduce the line in frames of varying sizes in two different ways. Subjects are asked to produce a line of the same absolute length (the “absolute task”), or of the same length, relative to the size of the enclosing frame (the “relative task”). Duffy &amp; Kitayama’s results (total N = 111) show that Japanese subjects perform better on the relative task, while American subjects perform better on the absolute task. Diagrams from Duffy, Kitayama, et. al., “Perceiving an object and its context in different cultures.”
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>These strategies of visual attention could explain why it is hard for me to imagine myself in the depicted space of <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em>. Entering an image requires mentally reconstructing the depicted space based on the the visual features of the image. Despite teamLab’s claims to the contrary, Western viewers do imagine themselves within perspective images.<sup><a href="#spatial-perspective-taking">4</a></sup> A 2006 study of facial recognition found that North American subjects were more sensitive to the intrinsic properties of facial features and Japanese subjects to overall facial configuration. Perhaps linear perspective feels natural to Western viewers because distance is encoded in size, an intrinsic property of objects which rewards focused attention, while in Ultra Subjective Space, distance is encoded in the overall configuration of objects, which demands dispersed attention.</p>
<p>Beyond this suggestive analogy between spatial and facial recognition, the construction of images in linear perspective and Ultra Subjective Space presupposes different conceptions of the self. Linear perspectives are calculated to reproduce the world faithfully from a single vantage point. This principle is dramatized in one of the earliest perspective images, a 15th century <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filippo_Brunelleschi#Discovery_of_linear_perspective">painting of the Florentine Baptistry by Filippo Brunelleschi</a>. Brunelleschi had viewers place their heads into a hood which cut off peripheral vision so that the painting could only be seen through a single pinhole. From this early beginning, linear perspective has demanded an autonomous, individual viewer: an independent self. By contrast, parallel projection can be understood as a sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riemann_sum">Riemannian sum</a> of perspectival views from infinitely many vantage points. The practice of showing the same place simultaneously at many different points in time, as in <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em>, further expands the number of viewpoints in Ultra Subjective Space. Feeling at ease with such an image requires a self capable of integrating these many viewpoints. Perhaps <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> is hard for me to enter and experience fully both because it presumes an unfamiliar conception of the self and demands unaccustomed habits of visual attention.</p>
<p>The sad irony of <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> and of my own means of appreciating it is not lost on me. Although teamLab announces that Ultra Subjective Space will bring, “New Spatial Awareness through Digital Technology,” the legitimation of Ultra Subjective Space by science in <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> comes at the expense of the lush Japanese details of the image. The cultural psychology research reassures me; it helps me believe as well as understand the truth of teamLab’s earnest arguments. Yet how bittersweet, that my conversion should come from reading social science research papers, rather than from the experience of the artwork itself.</p>
<p>The interactive projection <em>Sketch Town</em> allows me to enter and experience Ultra Subjective Space more fully by encouraging me to externalize the adoption of a new way of seeing. Participants in <em>Sketch Town</em> are invited to color in the outlines of familiar objects - fire trucks, houses, airplanes, UFOs - and then scan the crayon drawings. With my drawing scanned, I turn eagerly to a projected landscape which fills one wall, waiting for my creations to appear. Each crayon drawing is by itself spatially neutral; each airplane or car or truck could equally have been cut out of a linear perspective or an Ultra Subjective Space. Yet it is natural for Western viewers to imagine their object as belonging to a linear perspective image. When the drawing appears in the Ultra Subjective Space of the projected landscape, the viewer is forced to reconcile the assumption of perspective with the reality of Ultra Subjective Space. <em>Sketch Town</em> works because people are attached to their own creations, and rather than abandon their drawings in the unfamiliar territory of Ultra Subjective Space, viewers modify their visual expectations to accommodate it.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZVcWKBTVbvE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>High on an adjacent wall, a small perspective projection of the <em>Sketch Town</em> landscape highlights the strengths of the Ultra Subjective Space and helps make viewers conscious of their spatial habituation. This perspective projection draws on another familiar Western precedent - not the Renaissance painting, but the first-person shooter video game. Unlike a first-person shooter, however, there’s no way to control the vantage point. As the camera drifts through the scene, a glance at the Ultra Subjective Space representation underscores the limitations of this first-person view from which only a tiny fraction of the landscape is visible at a time, subject to the caprices of the camera’s motion. In the Ultra Subjective Space view, by contrast, it is possible to grasp relationships and to see that each entity has a well-defined role to play: UFOs move cars around, fire trucks extinguish burning buildings, and airplanes fight monsters. The juxtaposition of spatial modes in <em>Sketch Town</em> is an effective reminder that spatial recognition is acquired, and that there are alternatives.</p>
<p>All of this careful work to explain and evoke Ultra Subjective Space comes together in my favorite piece, an immersive video installation called <em>Crows are Chased and the Chasing Crows are Destined to be Chased as Well, Division in Perspective – Light in Dark</em>. More relaxed in its approach to spatial representation than either <em>Sketch Town</em> or <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em>, this piece honors Japan’s cultural heritage through references to the mythical crow <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three-legged_crow">Yatagarasu</a>, and in its re-interpretation of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BzXfVgYCxWI">Itano Circus</a>. This piece is less didactic, more lighthearted and eclectic, and I am able to appreciate it viscerally. Each time I stand in the middle of the dark room to experience the film, the joyful careening of the watercolor crows in the iridescent darkness impels me to move my body, to dance.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tjfDZP9YOcs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p><em>Crows are Chased</em> evokes this powerful response because of the way that it uses projection surfaces to convey a sense of space. One long wall serves as the main projection surface. This wall is partially obscured by freestanding walls on either side of the room which show fragments of the scene on the long wall behind, progressively magnified. By interleaving the projections with the inhabitable space of the gallery using these freestanding walls, teamLab gives the film a powerful three-dimensional quality. For a viewer standing at the back of the gallery, the rows of freestanding walls suggest a vanishing point at the center of the long wall, and the exaggerated size of the closer images creates a forced perspective which amplify the impression of depth. The camerawork is masterful as well; the camera swings and swoops as if it is yet another crow, chased and chasing. As flowers and crows spin from one panel to the next, they shrink in lurches and then grow large again, so that the forced perspective also exaggerates the whirling movement in the film. The floor, polished to a glossy obsidian, reflects these swooping animated figures in hazy washes of color which fill my peripheral vision. The result is neither linear perspective, nor Ultra Subjective Space, but some synthesis of the two.</p>
<p>I leave the gallery with a headache from the bright lights and strange odors and emerge blinking into a sunlit world of linear perspective. teamLab’s artworks haven’t fundamentally changed the way that I see the world. Truth aside, Ultra Subjective Space is a slogan with which teamLab hopes to rally a revolution against perspective. Yet, if it is to succeed, Ultra Subjective Space must be backed by more than naive revolutionary bravado, and it must be motivated by more than the vague promise of “a new kind of society.” For all its limitations and inherent biases, linear perspective is useful in the West - it is a cultural competency demanded and reinforced by mass culture. teamLab fails to provide a compelling reason to forego this cultural competency and adopt a new way of seeing the world.</p>
<p>In any case, the gallery may not be the best forum for teamLab’s utopian mission. As long as teamLab shows their work only in Menlo Park or New York City, charging admission of $20 a head, its reach will be limited both by geography and by affordability. Inoko has commented on the Ultra Subjective qualities of platform video games, saying that, “a life lived within Japanese spatial design may have been at root in the creation [by Japanese designers] of Mario and its distinctive style.” Video games cannot offer the immersive experience of installation art - but aside from <em>Crows are Chased</em>, teamLab’s large-scale installations in Menlo Park are mere glitz-and-glitter entertainments. There are plenty of platform games, but the rich, beautiful images in <em>Flowers &amp; Corpse Glitch Set of 12</em> and <em>Crows are Chased</em> suggest that teamLab has the unique artistic and technical abilities to create video games which celebrate Japan’s classical artistic heritage. Finally, video games using motion sensing and emerging VR technologies could bring powerful experiences of Ultra Subjective Space far beyond the gallery. teamLab’s show in Menlo Park leaves much to be desired, but their future is full of promise.</p>
<hr />
<p class="text-secondary">
Thanks to Abigail Kelly, <a href="https://abbylapier.com/">Abby LaPier</a>, Michael Webb, <a href="http://sallyfamacochrane.com/">Sally Fama-Cochrane</a> and Professors <a href="http://camilleutterback.com/">Camille Utterback</a> and <a href="http://haa.fas.harvard.edu/people/yukio-lippit">Yukio Lippit</a> for fruitful conversations and suggestions.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
For further reading, see <em>Cultural Modes of Seeing Through Cultural Modes of Being</em> (Duffy &amp; Kitayama), <em><a href="http://www.webexhibits.org/arrowintheeye/">The Psychology of Perspective and Renaissance Art</a></em> (Kubovy), and teamLab’s <em><a href="http://ultrasubjectivespace.com/">Dialogue between Toshiyuki Inoko and Yuji Yamashita</a></em> (Erimi), or see my <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1om4zfArwMVTKrA8iS_AbxxacKu0ptwX7BQOwhNGnT14/pub">full list of sources</a>.
</p>
<h5 id="notes">Notes</h5>
<div class="footnotes">
<p><a name="culture-and-the-self">1.</a> Markus, Hazel and Shinobu Kitayama. “Culture and the Self: Implications for Cognition, Emotion, and Motivation.”</p>
<p><a name="cultural-modes-of-seeing-55">2.</a> Duffy, Sean &amp; Shinobu Kitayama. “Cultural Modes of Seeing through Cultural Modes of Being” in <em>Social Psychology of Visual Perception</em>. 55.</p>
<p><a name="cultural-modes-of-seeing-57">3.</a> Ibid. 57.</p>
<p><a name="spatial-perspective-taking">4.</a> Tversky, Barbara and Bridgette Martin Hard. “Embodied and disembodied cognition: Spatial perspective-taking.”</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Three Excursions in Artificial Existence</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/three-excursions-in-artificial-existence/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/three-excursions-in-artificial-existence/index.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The creation of a true artificial intelligence is likely still decades away, but as limited forms of machine intelligence become increasingly ubiquitous, questions about the relationship between we humans and our semisentient creations will become ever more pressing. <a href="http://neat.thecjm.org/">NEAT: New Experiments in Art and Technology</a>, on view this past fall at the <a href="http://www.thecjm.org/">Contemporary Jewish Museum</a> in San Francisco, offered a few compelling explorations of artificial existence. Arranged among unremarkable interactive visualizations and video artworks, these artificial beings were both formally inventive and technologically topical.</p>
<p>The most emotionally arresting piece for me at NEAT was <a href="http://alanrath.org/">Alan Rath</a>’s <em>Forever</em>, a robotic sculpture with long brown feathers that could rotate forward and back on mechanized hinges. The feathers were attached at regular intervals to a lens-shaped frame leaning against the wall of the gallery; they looked like the legs of a giant beetle or the eyelashes of a great empty eye turned on its side.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LZigs_qFmkw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>When I turned the corner and saw <em>Forever</em> for the first time, I felt a flash of irrational fear. I’m not normally afraid or disgusted by insects, but my heart was pounding fast and hard as I stood in front of <em>Forever</em>. The movement of its many feathers, like the skittering legs of a giant, empty beetle, roused in me a primordial panic. The expressive power of this piece came from the way that the feathers moved in concert, sometimes undulating, sometimes flapping, then standing straight out and wriggling frantically before flattening abruptly against the wall again. The movement of the sculpture was purposeful, if unpredictable.</p>
<p><em>Forever</em> was a hybrid creature, an eerie combination of organic and mechanical materials. As such, this sculpture offered a tantalizing (and uncomfortable) sketch of the kind of biodigital being that some scientists believe represent humanity’s most promising future. The springiness of the quills made the sculpture lively as it moved, even as the natural brown-and-white patterning of the feathers recalled the hapless pheasant or turkey from which they originated. <em>Forever</em> was an alchemical creation, one which appropriated and reconfigured the discarded artifacts of one creature in order to create a new being. The resulting creature was both beautiful, and a bit melancholy: pinned to the gallery wall like a framed insect, the sculpture appeared almost as if trying to climb the wall, to flee the museum. I was both fascinated and repelled by <em>Forever</em>, and I found that I couldn’t look at it for long before discomfort pushed me away.</p>
<p><a href="http://salvagione.com/">Paolo Salvagione</a>’s <em>Rope Fountain</em> was a welcome relief from the intensity of <em>Forever</em>. Salvagione had constructed a sequence of sculptures, each consisting of a loop of white rope spun rapidly by a motor on the floor. Each loop appeared almost motionless, hanging in midair, its movement betrayed only by a penumbra of vibration about its silhouette and the humming of its motor. Each motor was on a pivot which allowed it to rotate parallel to the wall behind it. In addition, each motor had a nozzle controlling where the rope came out which was allowed to move forward and back. The regular motion of the motors along these axes caused the rope to move in unpredictable ways, swaying from side to side, stretching out horizontally, or rearing up to hit the wall behind.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/rope-fountain-combined.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
<em>(Left)</em> The rope was drawn into each motor at the bottom, and spun out again via a nozzle at the top. The motor and the nozzle were both free to pivot 180 degrees. <em>(Right)</em> Rapid rotation allowed each rope to twist and turn in midair.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The strength of <em>Rope Fountain</em> was the simplicity and transparency of the technology used to produce its complex, lifelike behavior. Standing in front of <em>Rope Fountain</em>, it was natural for me to attribute human motivations to the actions of the rope sculpture: curiosity, hesitation. The sculptures weren’t in the least anthropomorphic in form, but in their behavior, they reminded me of nothing so much as a line of dancers, moving freely and unselfconsciously. When a loop of rope twisted to dab at the ground, then recoil, I was reminded of a ballet dancer, eyes closed, exploring the world with their feet. Each rope sculpture was a line drawing, animated and lifted from the page, sketching a schematic being into existence. Each sculpture was also a creator, intermittently leaving faint smudges on the wall which collected to form dusty halos behind each loop of rope.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XGHACdmT5TE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
</figure>
<p>The technology used to produce these pieces was old - just a few motors, some rope, and a set of timetables to regulate the movement of each motor and nozzle. By exposing the technological apparatus that animated each sculpture, Salvagione demystified their behavior and allowed each piece to appear self-sufficient, autonomous. In all this discussion of Salvagione’s piece, I’ve struggled with “each” and “they”, and I would be remiss if I failed to acknowledge that I’ve been describing <em>Rope Fountain</em> in the singular, trying to convey the essence of the ideal form realized in each spinning loop. In short, <em>Rope Fountain</em> used technology, but it was not about technology - this was a piece about artificial beings and which questioned the minimum of what was required to represent a being.</p>
<p>Rath’s second robotic sculpture, called <em>Soon</em>, was a single enormous jointed arm mounted on a tripod. A floppy pink feather, of the kind used to make feather dusters, was attached to the end of the arm. As with <em>Forever</em> and <em>Rope Fountain</em>, the sculpture was capable of only a limited range of movement: the arm could rotate on its tripod and extend and retract, while the feather at the end was able to pivot freely in three dimensions. The sculpture was cordoned off from viewers by a circular border, like a circus ring. It was elegant, ungainly, absurd, pathetic.</p>
<p>Oxford philosopher <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nick_Bostrom">Nick Bostrom</a> writes in <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=7_H8AwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Superintelligence</a>: “Normally, we do not regard what is going on inside a computer as having any moral significance except insofar as it affects things outside. But a machine superintelligence could create internal processes that have moral status…there is at least the potential for a vast amount of death and suffering among simulated or digital minds, and, a fortiori, the potential for morally catastrophic outcomes.”</p>
<p><em>Soon</em> suggested the possibility of a tension between the dual nature of artificial entities as tools created for human benefit, and as autonomous beings in their own rights. The robotic sculpture was far from a superintelligence - indeed, the feather duster attachment riffed on the dumb domestic devices that are ubiquitous today: dishwashers, dryers, washing machines, and vacuum cleaners. <em>Soon</em> was no more than a simple machine. Yet the gallery setting and the circus ring-like enclosure reframed the appliance as an actor, an individual (though a bit of freak): worthy of attention.</p>
<p>Sometimes, <em>Soon</em> would dance, spinning gracefully and then stretching to unfurl its feather with an elegant flick. These were the movements which seemed to elevate the robot above the level of “device”. Yet, at other times, <em>Soon</em> performed an absurd sketch of domestic labor, senselessly and ineffectually dusting the air before rotating to begin again. The circular movements of the arm, tracing the outline of the ring on the floor, echoed this temporal loop in which the device was trapped. It was the contrast between these two attitudes which made <em>Soon</em> appear forlorn, futile, pathetic. Strange as it seems, I almost felt able to sympathize with <em>Soon</em>.</p>
<figure>
<div class="youtube-container">
<iframe class="youtube-video" width="100%" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h4Q6i_ic2uQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
<!-- .youtube-container -->
</figure>
<p>Missing from any of these works (though handled beautifully by <a href="http://camilleutterback.com/">Camille Utterback</a> in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cmKSwen2GAw"><em>Entangled</em></a>) was a convincing mode of interaction. Both of Rath’s pieces hinted at the possibility of interactivity, with <em>Soon</em> seeming to dust the noses of viewers, and <em>Forever</em> fluttering in time with sounds from the gallery, but in both cases the link between the environment and the actions of the sculpture was so subtle that it was unclear whether the appearance of responsiveness was due to accident or intention. Salvagione’s <em>Rope Fountain</em> didn’t offer even the suggestion of interactivity. The disinterested stance of these creatures was still compelling (though not altogether unfamiliar - think of teenagers or cats). Yet today, it’s the machines that can interact with (and track) us that are most interesting and frightening. Perception is an integral part of human existence; future artworks exploring artificial existence should use interactivity to engage this more deeply.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Death and Life of Dante-Harper Townhomes</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/dorchester-art-housing-collaborative/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/dorchester-art-housing-collaborative/index.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Chicago artist Theaster Gates bought an abandoned bank building for just $1 from the City of Chicago in 2013. Since then, his fans have eagerly awaited the debut of the <a href="https://rebuild-foundation.org/site/stony-island-arts-bank/">Stony Island Arts Bank</a>, an exhibition space and archive which opened in October to much fanfare. Though it’s an impressive demonstration of Gates’ fundraising chops (it cost $3.5M to make the building structurally sound), the building is architecturally underwhelming at present. Except for the lavish library at the back of the building, the Arts Bank is little more than an empty shell.</p>
<p>While <a href="http://www.dezeen.com/2015/10/03/theaster-gates-transforms-abandoned-chicago-bank-public-arts-centre/">design blogs</a> and Instagrammers slaver over the empty Arts Bank, an important project just two blocks South has gone largely unnoticed. This project, a renovated mixed-income housing development called <a href="http://dorchesterarthousing.com/">Dorchester Art + Housing Collaborative</a> (DA+HC), deserves attention. Gates and his nonprofit <a href="https://rebuild-foundation.org/">Rebuild Foundation</a> partnered with <a href="http://brinshore.com/">Brinshore Development</a> and architects <a href="http://landonbonebaker.com/">Landon Bone Baker Architects</a> (LBBA) to create DA+HC, and the playful, generous redesign by LBBA makes it a star example of mixed-income housing redevelopment in Chicago. DA+HC is an important step in Gates’ overarching project to turn Greater Grand Crossing into a cultural hub.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/greater-grand-crossing-map.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Buildings owned by Gates or hosting Rebuild’s programs are marked in blue on this map. The map shows the corner of Greater Grand Crossing where Gates has focused his attention.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Once a bustling working-class neighborhood, Greater Grand Crossing was hollowed out in the 1960s and 1970s by white flight, and never fully recovered. The neighborhood today is poor (<a href="http://crime.chicagotribune.com/chicago/community/greater-grand-crossing#note-3">25% of residents are below the poverty line</a>) and sparsely populated. Brick walk-up apartment buildings and single-family homes front on Greater Grand Crossing’s quiet one-way streets. On a closer look, many of these buildings are neatly boarded up with weathered plywood. There are vacant lots on every block - not the trash-littered and graffittied asphalt lots of the proverbial “inner city”, but green plots taken over by grass. It’s a neighborhood that has seen hard times.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/2007-facade.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
DA+HC was closed down and boarded up in 2007. Image © 2015 Google.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Gates has sought to transform the neighborhood since he arrived in 2006. He recalled in a 2014 interview: “You know my block is a violent block…When I moved there, people didn’t want to visit…I was really determined for Sixty-Ninth and Dorchester to be the most important place in the city…There’s still extreme violence, and yet beautiful things should happen in black space, because violent things happen everywhere. Right?”</p>
<p>DA+HC sits on 70th Street between Dante and Harper Avenues in the middle of this community, across from an elementary school, a playground, and one of those verdant vacant lots. The housing complex was originally designed by the Chicago Housing Authority (CHA) in the late 1970s, and opened in 1981 with 36 units of public housing in seven two-story brick buildings.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/chicago-housing-authority-times.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
This birds-eye rendering of Dante-Harper Townhomes was featured in a 1981 issue of the Chicago Housing Authority Times.
<figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The buildings are arranged along the sidewalk to create semi-enclosed common spaces at the back, away from the street. These shared, sheltered outdoor spaces help foster a sense of community by providing a space for residents to gather. On the larger block, between Dante and Harper Avenues, the sheltered interior of the block is subtly divided into two smaller spaces by a building that is set back from the sidewalk. With ten (originally twelve) units opening onto each of these smaller spaces, this division creates outdoor spaces which are more sheltered and intimate, but still provide opportunities for community interactions.</p>
<p>The gaps between the buildings serve as passages which visually and acoustically link the sidewalk to the gardens in back, helping to integrate the residents into the social fabric of the neighborhood.</p>
<p>Simple variations in the plan of the CHA townhouses make the spare, undecorated facades attractive. The facades step gently to and from the sidewalk, creating elongated bays and shallow recesses to shelter the front doors. This articulation of the facade serves as a kind of economical decoration for the building, creating patterns of light and shadow and giving each unit a sense of individuality. The materials matter, too. The red bricks used to cover the facades of the townhouses are standard-size fired clay bricks, not the larger concrete bricks often used by the 1980s to cut labor costs. These construction details help the CHA units to blend pleasantly with the older brick apartment buildings and single-family houses on the neighboring blocks.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/2015-facade-closeup.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
The beveled corners, entryway niches, and modulations in the plan of the facade lend visual appeal to the spare brick wall.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The Dante-Harper Townhomes reflect the complex and sometimes contradictory history of the CHA with respect to race, poverty, and housing in Chicago. The townhomes were built by the CHA as a result of a court order following the 1969 housing desegregation case Gautreaux v. Chicago Housing Authority. Gautreaux required the CHA to increase its stock of low-income units; to build or acquire public housing in white areas of the city before further development in racial minority areas; and to ensure that 50% of residents in each new development were drawn from the local community. Dante-Harper Townhomes failed in at least one respect: by the time it opened in 1981, the neighborhood was 70% - 90% black (hardly the integration required by Gautreaux!), and the CHA was building less housing, not more, than before. Despite this, the buildings avoid the banal, “poverty-oriented look” criticized by housing historian J. S. Fuerst. Perhaps inspired by developments commissioned by the CHA during the 1950s and 1960s, the Dante-Harper Townhomes was well-designed to invest the lives of its residents with dignity and foster a sense of community.</p>
<p>The Rebuild partnership made a number of important changes to the townhome development which further improve it. First, the central four-units between Dante and Harper were demolished to create an art center. Rebuild Foundation determined from a neighborhood survey that there was a need for performance space in Greater Grand Crossing. In response to this need, the art center at DA+HC houses a purpose-built dance studio and a craft space. Both will be open to residents of the neighborhood and to the arts elementary school across the street.</p>
<p>The dance studio is a beautiful space, with a high ceiling, spring-loaded wood floor for dancing, and lots of light. The front and back walls are all glass, save a vintage sliding door in front, and the resulting visual connection between the front and back of DA+HC helps link the semi-private spaces behind DA+HC to the public life of the neighborhood.</p>
<p>The landscaping created by <a href="http://www.site-design.com/">site design group</a> in collaboration with LBBA, is another significant addition to the development. In the original design, the sidewalk at 70th and Dante stretches twenty feet from the curb to the front doors of the townhomes. In the redevelopment, the expanses of concrete are replaced by generous front yards.</p>
<p>In the back, LBBA has replaced the grass backyards of the original design, which opened directly onto the alley, with two rock gardens containing seating and landscaped with shrubs and young birch trees. The architects also introduced a fence and a sidewalk along the back of this yard, heightening the sense of enclosure by dividing it from the alley. The parking spaces along the alley are surfaced using concrete brick pavers, rather than asphalt, which, from the rock gardens, creates the impression of a terrace that extends beyond the sidewalk.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/back-garden.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
The rear of DA+HC encloses a rock garden planted with low shrubs and young birch trees.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Finally, some small details - mustard yellow doors and a crimson band at the roofline - provide a playful touch. In short, the interventions of the Rebuild / LBBA / Brinshore partnership complement the existing strengths of the building and strengthen the possibilities for community formation by improving the shared spaces.</p>
<p>Residents of Greater Grand Crossing and critics alike have wondered whether Gates’ ascendant practice will gentrify the neighborhood in which it is anchored. Historically, artists have often been in the vanguard of displacement in neighborhood change - in the words of art historian Rosalynd Deutsche, artists are “the ‘shock troops’ of gentrification.”</p>
<p>The twelve CHA units at DA+HC do increase the neighborhood’s stock of affordable housing - but when compared with the <a href="http://www.thecha.org/file.aspx?DocumentId=1419">358 units CHA delivered in 2014</a>, it’s clear that they are a drop in the bucket. DA+HC is, at best, a gesture towards affordability. The reality of Greater Grand Crossing, according to Gates, is that gentrification still seems an unlikely and distant danger to most people on the block. Gates says: “People wanna leave if they can, and people have a right to leave. It becomes tricky…am I trying to trick people into staying? What can I offer?”</p>
<p>Perhaps the best way to understand the strategic position of DA+HC in Gates’ practice is as an incubator - a word that Gates himself has used elsewhere. Gates has long been interested in building communities of Black artists. In 2013, Gates <a href="http://arts.uchicago.edu/article/arts-and-public-life-initiative-unveils-arts-incubator-washington-park">opened</a> the University of Chicago’s <a href="http://arts.uchicago.edu/artsandpubliclife/ai">Washington Park Arts Incubator</a> (WPAI), two and a half miles northwest of DA+HC. In the two years since it opened, WPAI has organized gallery shows by <a href="http://www.alexandriaeregbu.com/">Alexandria Eregbu</a>, <a href="http://www.carolinekent.com">Caroline Kent</a>, and other Chicago artists, run training programs for local high-schoolers, and hosted community events. In 2013, Gates and artist <a href="http://www.elizabmyrie.com/">Eliza Myrie</a> hosted the first <a href="http://blackartistsretreat.com/">Black Artists Retreat</a> (B.A.R.), which <a href="http://theastergates.com/section/382198_B_A_R_Black_Artists_Retreat.html">brought dozens of Black artists together</a> at Dorchester Projects for two days of conversation and collaborative work.</p>
<p>At the Arts Bank, Gates has collected a vast (though uncatalogued) archive of Black history, literature, and media. Rebuild has a rotating artist residency program which brings artists to the neighborhood for a few weeks. Each resident artist is asked to use Rebuild’s collections at the Arts Bank in the work they produce during the residency.</p>
<figure>
<img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/739/21743204778_9e7f76425c.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Looking down into the atrium of the Stony Island Arts Bank. The pillars around the atrium are a temporary installation by artist Carlos Bunga. Photo by Steven Vance.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Unlike B.A.R. or the resident artists hosted by Rebuild Foundation, DA+HC is a sustained intervention which can be a source of stability and longevity for the artistic ecosystem in Greater Grand Crossing. Hopeful residents must apply to a panel of community members, and artists are given priority. Rebuild Program Manager Demecina Beehn says that DA+HC currently houses eight artists and curators, including a ceramicist, a filmmaker, and a makeup artist. In this way, DA+HC will bring artists who have a long-term involvement with the community - and, Gates is betting - with Rebuild’s collections. The <a href="https://twitter.com/outoftheyards/status/653244188155187200">best piece</a> at the debut of the Arts Bank was not an artwork by Gates, but a monumental installation in cardboard by Portuguese artist <a href="http://www.cgrimes.com/artists/carlos-bunga/offsite_exhibitions/">Carlos Bunga</a>. Similarly, in years to come, Gates’ most important work may come to be not his framed <a href="http://theastergates.com/artwork/2819882_Teleological_Study_with_Hose.html">fire hoses</a> or <a href="http://theastergates.com/artwork/2819859_Ain_t_I_a_Man.html">tar paintings</a>, but the artistic activity he fomented on the South Side of Chicago.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>A Sunroom of One's Own</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/a-sunroom-of-ones-own/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/a-sunroom-of-ones-own/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-05-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-05-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s a clear, warm Saturday morning in May, and my sunroom is full of light and the sounds drifting up from the sidewalk. Across the street, a black dog turns the corner sedately, trailing his human behind. On the sidewalk just below, a mother pushing a yellow stroller passes an elderly woman trundling a wire cart full of grocery bags.</p>
<p>Looking out from my sunroom, I can see the flat roof of Kimbark Plaza, just a block away to the south. In the other direction, twin rows of Victorian houses line South Woodlawn Avenue to the north. A block away along East 52nd Street, I can see the low profiles of modern townhomes built during urban renewal in the mid-1960s. As the sidewalk ballet—the stroller, the dog, the car alarm—plays out below, these taciturn buildings echo the stories of a century of history in Hyde Park.</p>
<p class="divider">
◊
</p>
<p>Hyde Park originated as a quiet, rural suburb of Chicago, and remained that way through the 1880s. A Mrs. E.G. of Hyde Park recalled, “We came here, that is my husband and I, in [1892]. It was regular country, with great meadows, wide dusty roads, and a bit of rolling country over to the southwest.” Another Hyde Parker—Mrs. Bennett, of 5807 South Blackstone Avenue—recalled, “The houses were large and spacious and surrounded by extensive lawns…. Most of the families kept cows and chickens.” This was a time when “mothers [of Hyde Park] worried for fear their children would fall into the water or get lost in the woods.”</p>
<p>The Columbian Exposition of 1893 set the stage for the urbanization of Hyde Park. In the years leading up to the Exposition, the Windermere, Del Prado, and other luxury hotels rose along the lakefront to house the fair’s wealthiest visitors. Further inland, smaller hotels, apartment buildings, and boarding houses were built between East 51st and 57th Streets in the heart of Hyde Park to serve as worker housing.</p>
<p>History books inform us that the Exposition brought more than 27 million visitors to Hyde Park, along with hordes of workers who built the fair’s “White City” and staffed the amusements on the Midway. Yet after the six-month run of the Exposition was over, and the crush of workers and visitors subsided, the fair’s enduring legacy in Hyde Park was a surplus of poorly designed and undesired buildings left behind.</p>
<p>“Hyde Park had been overbuilt in both apartments and homes during this hectic period,” wrote Paul Raymond Conway in his 1926 dissertation on Hyde Park apartment buildings. “The demand for housing accommodations fell [so much]…after the fair closed and the hard times came that entire buildings were sometimes devoid of tenants…so severe had it been that very very few apartments were erected during the next 10 or 15 years. It was a period of consolidation and recovery.”</p>
<p>The buildings had gone up in such a rush that the residents of Hyde Park had little time to think about them. As one woman recalled in 1926, “[The hotels] were put up very quickly for the fair trade, and were not considered a part of the neighborhood at all.” In the frenzy of the fair, many longtime residents of Hyde Park had believed that the tenements and hotels would vanish along with the visitors once the fair was over. Ruth R. said, “For 30 years people have been saying, ‘Of course they are horribly ugly buildings, but they are only temporary.’” The continuing presence of these leftover buildings—dirty, ugly, and full of “undesirables”—served as a warning of what Hyde Park might become if the process of urbanization were allowed to continue.</p>
<p>Even the apartment dwellers disliked the tenements. One student remembered: “I hated the apartments when I first lived in them, for I was so lonely and had so few friends. Again, my room was dark—oh, how I hate gloom!—as it had only one window that was surrounded (obscured) by another flat only about six feet away, and I could never see anything but a blank, grimy brick wall…flats are such ugly, straight, inartistic buildings.” Another resident said, “[An apartment] is so crowded, ugly, too dangerous to life and morals, and it is unhealthful.”</p>
<p>By 1910, apartment buildings were the only way to house the mass of families moving into Hyde Park. Many of these new arrivals were middle- and upper-class Chicagoans leaving deteriorating neighborhoods to the north and west. They were likely drawn to Hyde Park because of its bucolic condition and its excellent rail connections to downtown Chicago (at that time, the streetcar, the El, and the Illinois Central all passed through Hyde Park). The urbanization of Hyde Park first acquired urgency between 1910 and 1930. The population of Hyde Park nearly doubled between 1900 and 1920, and continued to grow rapidly through 1930.</p>
<p>The six-flat walk-up apartment, with its characteristic front sunroom, was developed during this time in an effort to make apartment living more desirable. These buildings are Hyde Park mainstays. Today, six-flats are typical Hyde Park student apartment buildings. These buildings are so called for their six apartments (two per floor). All residents of the six-flat enter the same door from the street and climb a central staircase to their apartments. Each landing opens onto two apartments.</p>
<figure>
<!-- This image shows Numbers 906-910 Ainslie Street.-->
<img src="./images/historical_sunroom_plan.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
This photograph and the corresponding floor plan show an apartment in Uptown which was listed in a 1917 “Directory to apartments of the better class along the North Side of Chicago.” Note the rectangular “solarium” marked on the plan at the front of each apartment; these rooms were also sometimes called “sun parlors.” Courtsey of <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101078303375;view=thumb;seq=5">HathiTrust</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The apartment is usually organized with the public spaces—dining room, living room—at the front of the apartment, by the street, a sunroom projecting from the front of the building opening off the dining room and living room. The bathrooms and bedrooms, the private spaces of the apartment, open off a long hallway stretching from the entrance to the back of the apartment. Except for the large, boxy sunrooms in front, this layout was typical of apartments across the country.</p>
<p>The sunroom was Chicago’s unique solution to the problems of city life. In a typical tenement building, each resident’s apartment was discernable from the sidewalk only as a dark window in a flat wall, indistinguishable from its neighbors. The protruding sunroom bays of the six-flat apartments made the internal division of the apartment building intelligible from the street. The pitched roofs capping the third-floor sunrooms recalled the proud Victorian houses of South Kenwood Avenue and South Drexel Boulevard. The flexibility of the sunroom, as well as the extra light it brought into the apartment (a remedy to the darkness of the earlier tenements), no doubt contributed to its popularity as a building type during this time. To this day, the sunroom acts as a buffer between the life of the apartment and the life of the street. It enables a connection to the outside world, but doesn’t demand it. Three walls of casement windows admit a panoramic view of the surrounding neighborhood. In the sunroom, the sounds of passing trucks, arguing couples, and barking dogs rise plainly from the street. Looking across to the sunroom bay next door, one becomes aware of next-door neighbors. I am more aware of the surrounding neighborhood in my sunroom than anywhere else in my apartment.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/sunroom_closeup_nighttime_darkened.jpg"></img>
</figure>
<p>The flip side of this is that, from the street, uncurtained sunrooms appear stagelit, their contents on display to all passers-by. For this reason, apartment dwellers seem to avoid their sunrooms. Despite this, the sunrooms provide the pedestrian with a sense of connection to the inhabitant within. The contents of a sunroom—a worn-out green sofa, a stack of books, a model ship—testify unavoidably to the life of its occupants. Through the sunroom, the pedestrian and the apartment dweller acquire a strange acquaintance in which neither sees the other, and yet each is aware of the other’s presence.</p>
<p>The addition of the sunroom made the apartment building interesting. Even more, the sunroom gave the apartment building the confident sense of place that, until then, had been enjoyed only by the single-family frame house.</p>
<p class="divider">
◊
</p>
<p>I’ve always found the modern townhomes lining East 55th Street unpleasant. Their (mostly) windowless faces seem unfriendly and the unrelenting beige flatness of the facades depresses me. Passing them on the sidewalk, I wonder to myself: Why are these buildings so bad?</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/im_pei_townhomes_liam_lee.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Modern townhomes by I. M. Pei stretching along 55th Street. Photograph by <a href="https://www.studioliamlee.com/about">Liam Lee</a> for <a href="https://www.chicagomaroon.com/greycity/">Grey City</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As it turns out, there are developments of modern townhomes all over Hyde Park—and they’re not all bad. Like the six-flat walk-ups built several decades before, these developments were conceived of as antidotes to the urgent problems that Hyde Park faced at mid-century. And like the walk-up apartments, the modern townhomes are artifacts of their time. Some of the solutions they introduced work beautifully today, while others appear alien and unsuitable.</p>
<p>Hyde Park was transformed through the intervention of community improvement organizations backed by the University and by federal and state initiatives. These groups used authority granted by newly expansive urban renewal laws to seize and demolish entire city blocks. Once the land was cleared, architects were brought in to realize in brick and concrete the planners’ vision for a new Hyde Park.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/55th_street_historical_comparison.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
55th Street and Lake Park Avenue, looking west. Left: <a href="http://photoarchive.lib.uchicago.edu/db.xqy?one=apf2-03950.xml">1955</a>, shortly before urban renewal; Right: <a href="http://photoarchive.lib.uchicago.edu/db.xqy?one=apf2-03954.xml">1961</a>, with prewar apartments and shops demolished and I. M. Pei’s towers in the middle of 55th street under construction. Courtesy of the <a href="https://www.lib.uchicago.edu/scrc/">Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The businessmen who put up Hyde Park’s walk-up apartments in the 1910s through the ’30s had accepted urbanization as inevitable. With the walk-up apartments they built and financed, they sought to accommodate the need for higher-density housing while providing apartment dwellers with privacy and a sense of individuality. The urban renewal authorities, by contrast, resisted the pull of urbanization. These authorities, led by the newly created South East Chicago Commission (SECC), sought to remake Hyde Park into a smaller, more tightly knit community attractive to young families with children. The architects hired to design the modern townhomes were tasked with interpreting and realizing this ideal.</p>
<p>The earlier six-flat apartment buildings had been criticized for their lack of neighborly feeling. Almost all of the modern townhome developments, like I.M. Pei’s townhouses and like The Commons, New Gardens, and Coop Square/Rochdale Place, sought to build a sense of community with courtyards and other common spaces.</p>
<p>Coop Square/Rochdale Place, a modern townhome development on the northern side of East 55th Street between South Dorchester and Blackstone Avenues, is a prime example of what the SECC sought to achieve. At Coop Square, Chicago architect Harry Weese gathered the units around an enclosed central courtyard with a sandbox and a tiny basketball court. Accessible only to the residents, the courtyard is a safe place for children to play and adults to relax. In front, there is a tiny strip of yard between the sidewalk and the front of the unit, where large windows allow residents to keep an eye on the street. This development is a safe haven for residents, but from the sidewalk, the locked gates and cast-iron fences pushed up to the curb are hostile and unwelcoming.</p>
<p>The Commons and New Gardens, two developments built after Coop Square/Rochdale Place in the mid-1960s, present a friendlier aspect to the street—perhaps because Hyde Park was by that time becoming a less threatening place. Both feature semi-public shared spaces. At New Gardens, south of East 55th Street between South Kimbark and Kenwood Avenues, units face onto two quiet, sunny courtyards. The courtyards spill down to the street over a wide, shallow flight of stairs. This small height difference gently marks New Gardens as a distinct community, without the tall fences and locked gates of Coop Square. The landscaped courtyard at The Commons, just north of Kimbark Plaza, is separated from the sidewalk by a modest brick wall and cast-iron gate. Both developments are clad in rough red brick, rather than the precast concrete and tan brick of Coop Square, and the textural richness of the brick and variation of the facade are a relief from the spare aesthetic that dominates East 55th Street.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/ben_weese_new_gardens.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
New Gardens modern townhome community, built in 1965 and designed by architect <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Weese">Ben Weese</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<img src="./images/ezra_gordon_the_commons.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
The Commons modern townhome community, built in 1965-1966 and designed by architects Ezra Gordon &amp; Jack Levin.
<figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Even I.M. Pei’s yellow-brick townhouses along East 55th Street that I so disliked were, I learned, responding in their own way to the circumstances of the time. So bleak and unfriendly from the sidewalk, these townhomes have generous back windows opening onto small private gardens. Many of the townhomes that Pei designed also share a semi-public central courtyard that, I can easily imagine, quickly becomes littered with bicycles, balls, and kids’ toys in warmer months. Inside, residents praise the, “efficient, warm, thoughtful use of space,” light, and “beautiful wood.”</p>
<p>Ironically, the shared spaces of the townhome developments often created community through conflict. Disputes between residents with children and those without were common: One resident of The Commons recalled the noise that local children used to make in the shared courtyard. She said, “Those kids would come out at seven o’clock in the morning. I said, ‘Oh my god, we got to do something about that.’”</p>
<p>“It was maddening!” said another resident. “[We] had meetings and explained the rules to the children. There was no bike riding and no ball throwing and no skating. They knew what the rules were, but you know…children are children.”</p>
<p>As an urban form, these courtyards reflected the collective unity of their residents in the face of the still-dangerous urban landscape. In the same way, the extreme flatness of the facades of Pei’s and Weese’s townhomes is harsh, but at mid-century it served as a statement of solidarity. The uniformity of these facades declared that the residents stood together as a bulwark against the physical deterioration of Hyde Park. If, today, walking along East 55th Street, the yellow-brick townhouses seem like fortresses, it’s because they once were.</p>
<hr />
<p class="text-secondary">
This article originally appeared in print in <a href="https://www.chicagomaroon.com/greycity/">Grey City</a>, the <a href="https://www.chicagomaroon.com/">Chicago Maroon</a>’s quarterly magazine (<a href="./files/Grey_City_Spring_2013_p02-7.pdf">pdf</a>). This article provided the source material for <a href="https://marthafrish.wordpress.com/2015/04/23/janes-walk-chicago-hyde-park-north-the-legacy-of-urban-renewal/">Jane’s Walks</a> in 2014 and 2015, focused on Hyde Park’s modern townhomes.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
Thanks to Diane Herrmann for speaking to me and showing me around her home, an I.M. Pei E-model townhome, and to Jewel Davis, who lives in a Hyde Park six-flat apartment, for speaking to me about her experience of the six-flat sunroom apartments.
</p>
<p class="text-secondary">
All photographs not otherwise attributed were commissioned for this article and captured by the skilled <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/fratmankel/">Matt Frankel</a>.
</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Permanence and Program: Farewell to the American Folk Art Museum</title>
    <link href="http://justinmanley.work/posts/farewell-to-the-folk-art-museum/index.html" />
    <id>http://justinmanley.work/posts/farewell-to-the-folk-art-museum/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-01-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Architectural critics and preservationists have been working themselves into a frenzy since the Museum of Modern Art announced last Wednesday its final decision to demolish the American Folk Art Museum building. MoMA’s announcement comes at the end of six months of extended deliberation, and MoMA has made it clear that this is their final decision. In light of this, the mainstream critics’ self-righteous outrage does more harm than good and obscures valuable insights into permanence, program, and flexibility in architecture.</p>
<p>The folk art museum building was designed by New York-based Tod Williams Billie Tsien Architects in 2001. Underlying the design was the belief that the building should be tailored to the character and needs of the institution it was to house and that form, materials, and structure should respond delicately and exactly to the program.</p>
<p>The façade of the building is paneled with heavy slabs of tombasil, an alloy which critic Herbert Muschamp likened to, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/14/arts/architecture-review-fireside-intimacy-for-folk-art-museum.html">“travertine marble alchemically rendered into bronze.”</a> The opacity of this façade and the rugged quality of its panels with their molten wrinkles and bubbles make a harsh contrast to the smooth glass façade of the MoMA next door. The façade of the Folk Art Museum is a gesture of solidarity with the art within, suggesting that the collection inside might be rougher around the edges, but also more sensuous and sincere than the modern stuff next door. The bronze face of the Folk Art Museum is a declaration of difference.</p>
<p>Inside, the architects created a winding pathway up through the museum, with extra-wide stairways displaying artwork and tall open spaces allowing views between different floors. Artworks are hung in unexpected places, and the sightlines through these tall open spaces let viewers experience pieces at different distances. Artworks are placed on balustrades and hung on concrete walls several stories up, as well as in traditional galleries. The collision of hanging styles made possible by the architecture captures neatly the mixed nature of the artifacts themselves.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/afam-interior.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Image from <a href="http://archatlas.net/post/120267532828">archatlas</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>At the same time, the architects sought to create a sense of permanence. Tsien said, “one of the things we learned is that we want, more and more, buildings that last. We want to avoid sheetrock and use <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/memory-palace">materials with resonance and character</a>.” The building is <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/culture/culture-desk/memory-palace">created using poured-in-place concrete</a>, which means that the walls, the floor, the ceilings are all essentially part of the same continuous structure. This type of construction has the feel of permanence as well as its actuality – concrete is one of the most difficult building materials to destroy. In addition, because every part of the building is structural, it is much harder to modify.</p>
<p>When the MoMA announced its intention to demolish the building, it cited the distinctive (i.e. non-glass) façade and the disconnect between the floor plates at the folk art museum and the MoMA next door. If it was the idiosyncrasies of the folk art museum that created the conflict, it was the deliberate permanence of the building that made the problem intractable, even after six months deliberation. The New York Times reported that, “Because the floor plates support the façade, a reconfiguration would require much of the building to be dismantled and reconstructed.” Elizabeth Diller of Diller Scofidio + Renfro <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/09/arts/design/a-grand-redesign-of-moma-does-not-spare-a-notable-neighbor.html">admitted</a>, “We can’t find a way to save the building. You pass a tipping point where there’s not enough of the original structure to actually maintain its identity.”</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/afam-dsr-rendering.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
Diller Scofidio + Renfro’s proposed replacement for the American Folk Art Museum.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>There is a sense, then, in which the building contained the seeds of its own destruction. The folk art museum building was designed to fit its original inhabitants forever, not to adapt – but change is inevitable. True; with a different purchaser, the building might have been repurposed despite its resistance to change. Even a building as idiosyncratic as the folk art museum might have been converted to offices, residences, or performance spaces. But the architects’ design philosophy gambled the flexibility and future of the building against the ideal of creating a perfect space for the folk art collection. The dreadful paradox is that what made the building great – the sense of permanence it evoked, the rich materiality of concrete and bronze, the unique interior spaces it created – also led to its destruction.</p>
<p>Those who have <a href="https://twitter.com/jerrysaltz/statuses/422020014141497344">vilified</a> the MoMA argue that, as a museum, the MoMA holds a public trust to safeguard the folk art museum building as a work of great architectural value. Some critics have even <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/09/arts/design/a-grand-redesign-of-moma-does-not-spare-a-notable-neighbor.html">imagined the building as an item in the MoMA’s collection</a>. This conception of the building is a mistake. Reducing the museum to an object, a piece of art, is to consider only its aesthetic and formal qualities, and to do so is to ignore those qualities which make it a building. A building is such because it is designed to be used: Vitruvius’ <em>utilitas</em>.</p>
<figure>
<img src="./images/afam-section.jpg"></img>
<figcaption>
The section drawing of the building reveals its idiosyncratic structure. Image from <a href="http://twbta.com/work/american-folk-art-museum">Tod Williams Billie Tsien Architects</a>.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The MoMA is demonized because its decision is judged by a standard which disregards the present context of the folk art museum in favor of the architects’ good intentions and the fit for the original occupant of the structure. The pens of the critics suspend the life of the building in the instant that it left the drawing board. But try as critics might to hold back the press of time, the fecund city pushes on relentlessly. The building must be judged in its current context, and part of that context is its usefulness as a space to be inhabited.</p>
<p>Ah, the protesters say – but the building would be perfectly useful if not for the damned expansion of the MoMA. Expansion is made a dirty word. Yet – if anything, expansion should be good. Paul Goldberger <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/architecture/2014/01/american-folk-art-museum-demolition">admits</a>, “MoMA is as compromised by overcrowding as any museum I know…Lowry [the director] envisions the expansion as a way of creating much needed breathing space.” So while the expansion of the MoMA is regrettable in its consequences, it is not the sign of moral corruption that critics would have us believe.</p>
<p>The MoMA must bear responsibility for the tragedy of the demolition of the folk art museum – and it is a tragedy, if only because the building was loved dearly by many museumgoers. But it should bear that responsibility as the sad result of a Hobson’s choice forced by the nature of the folk art museum and not as a badge of <a href="http://www.nybooks.com/daily/2013/04/12/momas-act-vandalism/">‘cultural vandalism’</a>.</p>
<p>The folk art museum was an eccentric, friendly building that enlivened and enriched the urban life around it – Herbert Muschamp once called it <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/14/arts/architecture-review-fireside-intimacy-for-folk-art-museum.html">“companionable”</a>. We cannot do without such structures, buildings that are dynamic, brave, and richly memorable. It is true that the construction of such precious buildings is a gamble, that it comes at a price – but the worst that could come out of this demolition would be a swing to the other extreme: in place of the folk art museum, a building that is generic and utterly all-purpose. We hope that, as it moves forward with plans for a new building, the MoMA will bear the responsibility of the demolition thoughtfully and look for meaning in its loss, mindful of the architectural promises and perils it embodied.</p>
<p class="note">
The cover image for this piece is by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/davidgalestudios/">davidgalestudios</a>.
</p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
